He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall and he will be the light of the
Nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled all who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him and they
Will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of spirits first Enoch chapter 48
Verses 4 through 5 the modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless
Haunted by spirits angels demons and saints
In our time, many yearn to break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see
and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Steven Damick and Father Steven DeYoung host
this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation, the union of the seen and
Unseen as made by
God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Greetings, dragon slayers and giant killers.
You're listening to the 147th episode
of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick and thrown
to the Palace of Podcasting in Raleigh, North Carolina.
And I'm not actually sure if with me or not
is Father Stephen DeYoung.
Well, the word with is functioning
in an interesting way in that.
It's true, since because I'm not
actually there with you. That's true. It's it's I don't know in
what sense are you with me? There's a sense in which you're
with us all Father Stephen. I mean, I'm not necessarily against
you.
You're not scattering abroad either. Yeah, I'm usually. Yes,
so the father's father Stephen, of course, is just
surfaced from the swamps, the steaming swamps of Lafayette
Louisiana and this is just
my eyes first. I did that. That's right. It is pretty eyes come up and look
balefully at everyone and then you emerge. We're live this time. We are live. And that
means that starting in second half, Mike repo man again. We'll be taking your calls
and also I have a question here. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Repo man in this case.
to the Emilio Estevez movie or to the lame professional wrestler.
Wow, I was actually making a reference to the person that comes and takes your stuff. If you don't pay for it as you like literally, oh, so you had neither in mind. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Well, I'm going to interpret it as being about the Emilio Estevez movie.
And I'm going to I'm going to do a couple of things. First, you know how every time one of these episodes goes up on YouTube, one of the first comments we get is that there's too many ads.
Yeah, yeah.
So, let me just comment that the song on the Repo Man soundtrack by Suicidal Tendencies
was awesome.
And now that I've said that, demonetized.
You're welcome.
There you go.
Watching this later.
That's true.
Yeah.
The other thing I was going to say is Repo Man is a good movie featuring Emilio.
Huh.
But not the best.
What do you think is the best?
You're probably thinking minute work with Charlie Sheen.
No, I say the nay. I had two other films potentially in mind. The greatest movie is
Free Jack
I have not seen that one. Okay. Well, it it has
Mick Jagger playing the villain
And it's just Mick Jagger wearing a big helmet
so he kind of looks like a cross between noodles from the gorillas and
and Gollum.
in the animated Rankham Bass Hobbit.
Wow.
So I mean, I have not seen enough
Emilio Estevez's filmography to say which is the best,
but among my favorites is the probably obvious,
very obvious pedestrian selection of the Breakfast Club,
but also actually a movie that I like much better than that
is The Way.
Have you seen that one?
The Way?
Yes, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, I liked The Way.
Typical.
I know.
He's barely in it though.
That's
true. That's maybe that's what's so great about it. He directed it, but he's barely
in it. Yeah. There's no big Jagger. There is no big Jagger. There usually isn't, which
is a huge strike. Yeah. But if you ever see him in a bar, you need to just yell, Emilio
across the bar. Well, this, this is our sixth anniversary episode. So, you know,
the shenanigans I begin I suppose to the day in fact it was on the
day, September 10th, 2020, that this show premiered. It was a day, a time we all remember with great
fondness and nostalgia. I know, right? Everyone hunkered down in their homes, cursing the government,
or their reckless neighbors or whomever they blamed for everything in their life.
And the next thought that somebody had was, hey, honey, let's listen to two bozos talk about
angels and demons and weird stuff in the Bible. And was that an Anselm sub-reference or
We're going for the clown go with that.
So here we are.
And those of you who said that to yourselves in 2020 have wasted six perfectly good years
of your life listening to ridiculously long podcast has probably taken years off of my
life for various kinds of reasons.
People are going to be mad about that too.
That's true.
It's true.
Some reason people get mad when we say that our own podcast is a waste of time.
I know it's like do you want to sit down?
Thank you so much for watching.
be self-effacing do you want us just come out to be like you're welcome for the
greatest podcast known to man right like at the end of each episode like actually
I just read in the chat that apparently we have someone tuning in from Tbilisi
in the Republic of Georgia I mean that's pretty amazing I can't even think of
what the time must be there right now it's got to be like ridiculously early
in the morning or maybe it's tomorrow I mean I'm sure it's tomorrow I'm
I'm just not sure when tomorrow.
It's like 4 a.m.
So what's up, Time Traveler?
Yeah, anyway, tonight, we're going to be looking at the list of biblical and also Bible adjacent texts that are going by the name of Ezra, which is probably a longer list than some of you thought.
But before we begin with that, in celebration of our sixth anniversary, I thought I would read some of our favorite reviews from the past six years.
So are you ready, Father?
Well, I do have to say, you just, again, you characterize this as some of our favorite reviews.
Oh.
But you picked them and I don't know which ones you picked.
ones you picked.
the royal. So these may or may not be some of my favorite reviews. Maybe it wasn't your
favorite reviews. Maybe they are some of Father Andrew's favorite and Mike's or I don't know.
Um, yeah. Anyway, uh, okay. So I'm going to read, I'm going to read a few. This first
one comes to us from June of 2023. So this is somebody who listened for like a couple
of years and they titled the review. Um, the Laura Spears podcast jumps the shark.
I'm not going to read the whole thing, just kind of one of the best.
parts. This is what our reviewer has to say. Whereas Miami Vice went from a slick cool blend of
music actions and aesthetics to a gritty cop drama. Lord of Spirits went from an offbeat but
informative discussion of the spirit realm to a blatant recruiting pitch for the Eastern Orthodox
Church with strong anti-Catholic overtones. So what do you rate that one, Father?
Well, so see that one is less entertaining to me because
it's technically accurate. Oh, okay. Okay. Yeah. Blatant recruiting pitch for the
east and north. Right. It became blatant. Like it was always always that. Right. Oh, no, we
won't ever. Blatant at a certain point. You found us out. Yes, two Orthodox priests think
you should be Orthodox, too. Shock shock. Who to thunk it. Yeah. Yeah. And here's
a classic that I know that you do love. Actually, you have told me you love this
one and this comes from
that great host of literary excellence, formerly known as Twitter, it says this, Stephen DeYoung
is the false prophet, Jonathan Peugeot is the beast.
Yeah, again, I mean, it's, I mean, the accuracy would diminish the humor, except for the
fact that they clearly have that reversed.
Yes, because you're the beast.
I am the Beast and Ed Pajot is the...
the faux profiteur, whoever he's got in French. I don't know.
That's right. Okay, so here's our third one for this half. And
I'm going to read this verbatim. I'm going to try. In this
episode, no reference to which episode to talk about. In this
episode, they moved to a more denominational weird beliefs
in an apologetic tone about the fake difference between
veneration of creatures and worship of Yahweh may Yahweh open
their eyes. Two stars. So there you go. Two stars. That one I think is inaccurate
finally. Okay. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, that's just way off base. Okay. Well, I don't even know
what show he was listening to. I don't know either. I don't know either. So with that
beginning out of the way, so we're going to get to it by starting with the men himself.
is Ezra, Father Stephen? Who is Ezra? I heard
recently, as I was why hers and say heard, I read recently, as
I was doing research for this episode that Norm McDonald, back
in the 1990s, had a joke in which he was listing off like the
top five, you know, musical hits of that day. This is number one.
But I'm not going to try to do a more Norm McDonald voice.
Number one, better than Ezra. Number two, Ezra, which is
just a good wholesome joke. I don't know. I like it. Not
not a
great impression. That's why I said I although I have it on really good authority out there
in the audience that if you give him money, he will impersonate Bruce Springsteen. That
is correct. That is correct. I can do a dead on Bruce Springsteen. And he did not give
any amount. So like shove a dollar in his pocket, right? Like not a Canadian dollar
Yeah, that's the thing born in the USA
Yeah, Canadians use fake money with birds on it. So, you know, they call their dollars loonies. I mean, that's real
Yeah, who so who is Ezra father?
Ezra
We're not referring to any of the
Ezra's in our contemporary culture because I said I was trying to try to do an Ezra joke and like all the Ezra's
I could think of our figures of public controversy and ignominy. So
all those jokes would take this to a dark place but
That dark dark place like the recent flash movie
But the the Ezra we're talking of course is the biblical Ezra
Now what do we say the Ezra who's in the Bible?
Over the course of this episode you're gonna realize just how complicated that sentence actually is yes
This will be so I think this is gonna be one of our most mind-bending episodes
With regards to the question of biblical canon
Yes.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yes. So buckle up. Yeah. Some of you have been presented with a very
clean view, a very orderly view that all of this is clear cut and everything. And as usual
lot of this show we're gonna we're gonna ruin that for you with nuance. So Ezra is this
central figure, we see just how central these traditionally of the post-exilic, the
immediately post-exilic period in the Old Testament. Now if you're working off of
the Hebrew Canon, the Old Testament Canon used by most Protestants.
then the post-exilic material of the Old Testament occupies kind of a weird place.
We're going to be talking a lot today about how significant Ezra is,
but I think in most people's experience who grew up with the Protestant canon,
you didn't grow up hearing a lot about Ezra.
Yeah, I don't think he's a like a big figure. I mean, people, you know, it's not Moses. He's not Elijah. Yeah
But he kind of is Moses
Yeah, right. He's that level of important
But but yeah, like in terms of you know, the last the last figure who you really get a lot of in
At least our era
See because father Andrew and I were born in the same year. So I'm using the us in the hour correctly
first. The Royal Hour. The last figure you really get in the Old Testament in most Sunday
school stuff is Daniel, which is basically exilic, right? Like in the exile, Daniel,
three Utes, right, and over there in Babylon, and then the Persians come.
But in Daniel, even though you get into the Persian period
by the end of the book of Daniel,
there isn't really a lot of talk in Daniel.
There isn't much of anything about the return
from exile or any of that, right?
So the post-exilic period tends to get kind of just left
off and you don't talk about it.
And I think that's in part because it occupies
this weird place in that
Um, it, it's.
It's sort of like because the Protestant canon makes the Bible like a donut.
There's this hole in the middle that's referred to usually as the inter-testamental period.
Yes, right.
Right.
Or though sometimes...
This is not just me asserting something.
I mean, Protestants all recognize this.
There's this blank spot.
400 silent years.
Yes.
There's this.
trunk that gets skipped over, right?
And by comparing it to a doughnut, I'm saying the whole I'm presenting is if the hole were deliberate, right?
So
There's this sort of skip far and
you know, if you're gonna skip that history
having the very beginning of the post-exilic period in
there
Right before you cut time
right right before you blank out is kind of odd right it's like watching all of
Star Wars that's the name of the movie and then watching like the escape from
Hoth at the beginning of Empire Strikes Back and then skipping to return to the
Jedi yeah you'll never see General Viers right like it makes more sense to
watch the whole thing but if you're not gonna watch the whole
thing. You'd probably have a better movie going experience
skipping the whole second movie, right? Like why watch the
beginning? Just go straight from Star Wars to return to the Jedi,
right? So there's just sort of it just sort of ends, right?
They return from exile and then it's sort of over. It makes
little more sense from the perspective of the Hebrew canon, right? So from a rabbinic Jewish
perspective, ending there makes a little more sense for a couple of reasons. Number one,
they deliberately excluded anything that had to do with the Hasmonean period.
Yeah, which is why we have the interesting irony that
at least for, you know, the feast of theirs that most Christians have heard of.
namely Hanukkah is in the Christian Old Testament, the Orthodox Christian Old Testament, but is not
in the Hebrew Bible. Right. Because everything having to do with that gets, and even in the
celebration of Hanukkah, they're not talking about Judas Maccabius or anything. Right.
Right. Like they're not talking about the Maccabees. Because two centuries of
of zealotry, ended with the destruction of Jerusalem, and...
the near destruction of the Jewish people by the Romans, right?
So that was seen as failed, right, I feel like.
So that not being included, they're not including that their scriptures makes perfect sense, right?
And so from their perspective, they're sort of still living in the era that began with the return from exile.
They're not in exile in Babylon anymore, but they're also still kind of in exile because
they're ruled
over by other people. Right? So the Hebrew can and kind of ending
there kind of makes a little more sense, right? But it creates
this weird effect when you attack the New Testament onto the
onto the end of it without any of the intervening material. And
so there's no there's no sort of clear event there that says
This is where it should end, right?
It's not like that's the end of the Ezra material
is this satisfying ending.
Oh, now it's all wrapped up.
They're back in the land, and everyone's happy.
No, they're not, right?
That's not where it ends.
And then, sort of, relatedly, this material...
Which is the Ezra material in
In the Hebrew canon in the pros and canon the book of Nehemiah. We're gonna get into that more in our second half
The last couple of prophets, especially Malachi in the book of the 12, which is what the collection of the minor prophets
was referred to as
Anciently the book of Esther
The book of Daniel for that matter which ends in the Persian period all of this stuff that goes into these texts to go to the
period. And we're going to be doing going into this the rest of
tonight that with the Ezra material, but all of it, there's
like multiple versions of the text. Yeah, right. Like there's
couple versions of Esther. Couple two, three versions of
Daniel. Right. As we're going to see a bunch of different ways
of putting together Ezra material. Isn't kind of a rec as
as well.
Yeah, and that's just during the exile. Yeah. But so all of this late stuff, that also keeps
it from being a sort of satisfying ending to the Old Testament in that none of it is structured
in that sense. You have, through the Old Testament up to that point, there's this very clear
through line.
Right of
Here's the Torah
Right lays everything out sets the basis for everything. Here's the history of Israel as they fell into disobedience
Northern kingdoms wiped out
Judah goes into exile
There's a promise that God is going to restore them
Right, and then there's some material that talks about oh well here's the beginning of them sort of halfway kind of being restored
But not really
You know, like it doesn't fit the overall sort of arc of the Old Testament.
So basically this is our introductory way of saying, this stuff's kind of a mess and
we're going to wade through that mess now for the next couple of hours.
Enjoy.
Just two hours?
All right.
I'm in.
I said couple.
You
couple, two, three. And I said next couple. Oh, okay. So who knows? All right, I'll stop.
So remember, the show was originally supposed to be like 45 minutes, 45 minutes to an hour.
That was the original. We've never achieved that. Never. A couple. I don't even think
the first episode, I think we even ran over an hour on the first episode. And I think
I think a couple of the episodes that you did is...
as solo pre-records, I think.
Oh yeah, where I just read a couple of stories.
Yeah, they're like 15, 20 minutes.
Yeah, yeah, I should point out,
but those are bonus episodes.
That's true.
And I can prove that they're bonus episodes
because this is episode 147.
It is our sixth anniversary.
That means you guys have gotten two extra episodes
beyond what we promised at no additional charge.
That seems, yeah, likely.
So, okay, we've prepared you for the fact this is going to get messy. Now I will finally
begin to answer Father Andrew's earlier question. Who is Ezra?
Yes.
It's Ezra we're talking about. So traditionally he's always been referred to in Jewish and
Christian tradition as Ezra the scribe.
Okay, so he's a literate human.
Yes, but
Scribe, remember, you know, again, we're more familiar with this from the New Testament,
but you know, where there are the scribes and Pharisees, right?
So it wasn't just in general that he was literate.
He was literate and he was one of the people who was maintaining and preserving and involved
with the Torah and the other sacred writings in particular.
And a lot of the study of these texts was really the hand-copying of these texts, right, as a way of becoming very intimately familiar with them.
Ezra was also a priest, so he's a Levite, he's descended from a line of priests, he is a priest.
Ezra in English is derived original.
from the Hebrew Ezra Yahoo, which means Yahweh is my helper or assistant. And of
course it's not, you know, the one who assists me, not my, you know, my secretary.
If anything, the reverse. That gets translated into Greek as estrus.
And that's where the Latin esdras comes from.
So we're going to be talking about first esdras,
second esdras, first esdras,
second esdras, third esdras, fourth esdras,
fifth esdras, sixth esdras.
So many esdras.
And then some more esdras after that even.
But that's where the esdras spelling comes from
is it comes from Latin through Greek.
Yeah.
So traditionally,
This first one's gonna be a shocker. Ezra wrote the book of Ezra
But also traditionally and we'll talk about this a little more he edited
What is now called the book of Nehemiah, he wrote first and second Chronicles, and
And there is a tradition there's a line of tradition in the Talmud and
Saint Jerome says this too. They have to remember the Babylonian Talmud came
together fully around 580. And Saint Jerome is a century before that going
to study Hebrew in Bethlehem. So Saint Jerome probably got this tradition about
out from there, from Jewish circles.
in Palestine at that time. But that strange Jewish tradition and Saint Jerome say that he also wrote
Malachi. Wait, how can that possibly be? That was overly dramatic. I'm feeling a little overwrought
these days. What can I say? So long as it's not undercooked. So
I mean, I'm in a subtropical climate as you yourself are even more than I am so
undercooked is definitely not a problem here.
Yes.
So, the idea there is that Malachi is not a proper name, that Malachi is a title.
And it is, of course, Malach E in Hebrew, Malach being the word for messenger or angel.
And so...
the E would be a possessive be my messenger. Right. So the idea is that that's a title under
which Ezra wrote that prophetic book. It's going from Saint Jerome. Now that said, that said,
I don't buy it. Okay. Okay. I love Saint Jerome. I'm right now looking at an icon of Saint Jerome.
Oh, nice.
In this very office with his line.
But Saint Jerome has a bunch of interesting and odd ideas about who wrote what in the Bible.
That is true. Although my favorite Saint Jerome comment is about Pelagius.
Where, do you know about this one?
Does this involve a certain Scottish food stuff?
That is correct. Have you heard me say this before? Basically, he says,
I think the way it gets translated is something like, you know, that Pallagian is
is the result of him being too full of what gets usually translated as Scottish
porridge, which basically means that the guy ate so much haggis that he came up
with a heresy in which you can save yourself without the help of God. So what
should that tell you about haggis boys and girls? Just putting that out there.
Anyways, I mean to be fair to him if you can suggest successfully digest that
much haggis.
I hate you.
I hate you do.
I know, I have been to Scotland and had Haggis multiple times, and on a couple of occasions
given to me by a bishop. So I feel it.
Yeah, so in terms of biblical books, Saint Jerome also says that Saint Matthias, who's
chosen in Acts to replace Judas, wrote the Gospel of Matthew at one point. So sometimes
the next video.
Thanks for watching.
I'll see you next time.
Bye, friends!
I hope you have a great day.
I'll see you next time.
Bye bye.
Bye.
just has an interesting idea about authorship.
He's not getting this one from nowhere.
We kind of know he's getting it from a strand of Jewish tradition,
but even the Talmud is divided on that. Yeah.
That's just one strand of tradition in the Talmud.
So I wouldn't put a ton of stock in it.
Okay. That Ezra wrote Malachi.
I think Malachi is a separate person whose name was probably Malachi.
So, Ezra also, in addition to being a priest, there is, shall we say, a strong tradition
that he was the High Priest of his day.
Now, that may or may not be in the Bible, that we're going to explain what that means
when we get to the second half.
But even if it's not, not only is there a long-standing good fur-
by lots of ancient sources, tradition of this, but it just also kind of makes common sense
in the sense that he is a priest, that is in the Bible regardless, right? So he's a priest.
He is the priest who is in the highest position of spiritual leadership in Judea among the returnees.
Yeah, he's clearly the big cheese. It is time. If he's not the high priest, there's no one
else mentioned who is? Anywhere in scripture or anywhere else?
So, it seems pretty safe to conclude that he was in fact the High Priest, even if you're
a person who somehow comes to the conclusion that the Bible doesn't explicitly say it.
In terms of when we're talking about here, historically, I know we said post-exilic,
but that covers some range.
So Ezra was sent by Arta Xerxes back to Judea, what was soon to become.
the Persian province of Judea in 457 BC. You were tech. Yeah. And he brought more
returning exiles with him. So there had already been a couple of waves of returning
exile to the land. He's sent there by Arta Xerxes to kind of gather them
together and sort of establish more of a community there.
constitute them sort of religiously and culturally. And then in 444 BC,
which is 13 years later, if you're not good at math,
Nihomayo was sent by Artaxerxes to be the
first
governor of the Persian province slash Satrapi of Judea.
Okay, so Ezra coming is part of the process of making this
an official Persian province political unit but Ezra is functioning as a
religious and cultural leader. Nehemiah is sent. He is the actual representative of
the Persian government and he's said to have been a cupbearer of the Persian
Emperor. It's not clear whether that was literally his job or if Cupbearer is
just being used there to indicate he's a minor.
court official of some type, right. But he, though Jewish, had a some kind of lower level
court position under the Persian emperor, and that's why he's chosen to be the first
governor for the new province. And once he's there, Ezra does a lot of things that become
majorly in
important. And because we just get this little, like we said, in the Protestant canon or in
the Hebrew canon, you just get this little taste of Israel and then your Old Testament
stops. You don't get a full sense of it. But a lot of the things that are sort of
in full motion centuries later when we come to the New Testament, right?
they're being a Sanhedrin so Ezra forms what sort of the proto-Sanhedrin the
the great assembly that ends up becoming the Sanhedrin later the assembly of the
elders of the people right he forms that he's the one who begins the
synagogue system right of worship of having meeting places scattered
around in villages.
The rebuilding of the town.
is undertaken at this time too. We're going to talk here in a second, a little more about that,
but he's the one, so all the synagogues that are around in the New Testament, right? The beginning
of that process is with Ezra, we don't write then get the rest of that process, right? If you
just skip then to the New Testament, it's just all there, right? And so this is part of what
we meant, what we alluded to right at the beginning, we were talking about how important
Ezrae.
is, in terms of the history of Judaism, Ezra is probably the second most significant figure
after Moses.
Yeah, I mean, he's basically a kind of re-founder of, you know, the, well, in this case, Jewish
nation, not just is not Israelite.
It's it's this is really the point where you get, you know, Jews as a distinct thing.
Yes.
Yeah.
And yeah, so this is he is the transition point right before this you have Israelite religion
After Ezra, you have Second Temple Judaism. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah that we're always talking about on the show
right, I mean you have
Judaism as a as a concept. Yeah, right. Yeah, right. I mean I would say it's it's worth at this point
remembering everybody, that if you say, you don't, you don't
know, it's not correct to refer to most of the history of God's people in the Old Testament
as Jewish, because the Judeans, the Jews are only one tribe of Judah. But this now, you
know, the return from the exile, basically what you have left is that one tribe.
Right. And some Levites and some Benjaminites, but mostly, yeah. And the new entity that
forums is called Judea right not just the political
entity. But the people, the people now through Ezra, that's what's happening in the book of Ezra.
And we'll discuss what that is more here in the second half. But what's happening is he is forming
Jewish identity, because the word that we translate as Jewish or Jew, right, is actually
Judean. Right, right, right.
Judea is not Jews, it's Judeans.
Okay. But it's Judean, not just again as I'm a person who lives in Judea, right? Who lives within
this province of the Persian slash Greek slash Roman Empire. It's there, there are Judeans after
Ezra who never set foot in Judea, right? There are Judeans who live their whole lives in Alexandria.
Egypt, who lived their whole lives in Mesopotamia, later on who lived their whole lives in Greece,
but they're Judeans, because what Ezra does is he fundamentally re-orients what that identity
is about in order to focus it on Torah observance.
So in ancient Israel.
in ancient Israel
What being an Israelite was about?
Right, we've talked before
Ritually, yes, you have circumcision
Right as this right of initiation if you're a woman you're married to or the daughter of a circumcised male
You have
The celebration of the feasts
Right when if you were able you went to Jerusalem
And especially Posca, that was the highest priority one, Passover, right?
That's what the religion was focused on, and you brought sacrifices to the temple.
So it's about what God you worshiped and not only how but where you worshiped him.
Judaism that is forming now, right, among the Judeans.
Judean identity is about the way you live your life wherever you live it and that you're living your life
Keeping Torah following the commandments of the Torah now. That's not ignoring the temple
Right because part of those commandments is the feasts the sacrifices right so those are all there too
But they become less the focus the place of the temple
gets relativized within this ethos. Yeah. And that's why you can have the
synagogue system. This is when you have synagogues which were not just a house
of worship, they were like a community center essentially, right, with a house
of worship in it. The synagogues in all of these cities, right, where people
would get.
gather on the Sabbath for what? For the reading of the Torah and the other scriptures, right?
And to sing Psalms and to do these other things. That begins with Ezra.
Yeah, I mean, prior to that, you have basically the the festival celebrations going on at
the temple, but unless you were
a priest or a Levite working inside that thing. And then before that, the tabernacle, you didn't
see what was going on. Like you'd bring your sacrifice and hand it to the priest and then
stand there and wait for him to bring it out later. And he'd bring you some of the
meat liquor. Yeah. And that's what you did with your family. You weren't standing there
watching them pray. You certainly weren't saying they're watching them offer sacrifices.
You might smell the sacrifices. Yeah. And that's that's the big disconnect. Oh,
experience a lot of times with a lot of
our Protestant friends like if you start talking about why the Orthodox Church doesn't use musical
instruments really I don't even get the nitpicky stuff why we don't really use musical instruments
in worship they're like well what about the temple worship and I always ask what does temple
worship mean to you yeah yeah the people didn't all go every Sabbath to the temple like I mean
most of them physically couldn't right if they wanted to they've lived miles and miles away
right and Deuteronomy takes that into account.
It's the way it changes some of the commandments regarding sacrifice and stuff
There weren't public worship gatherings on the Sabbath in ancient Israel these things happened within families, right?
Like you'd have weddings. You'd have there were the elders of
the tribes and clans would preside over them, right, but
There was
like a place you went once a week right until the synagogue system starts with
Ezra yeah yeah exactly and you know I'm gonna poke a little at our
Protestant friends here right I thought this is a Catholic show yes I know this
is supposed to be the anti-Catholic show but here I am poking our poor
Protestant friends scriptures are very important to you you know and
And, you know, especially like our Presbyterian friends who have the
regulative principle of worship, you're supposed to worship the way the Bible tells you to.
You guys worship is drawn from the synagogue system.
And the synagogue system is not commanded or even described in any kind of detail in your Bible.
An extra biblical tradition.
Because it's in the doughnut hole.
Yeah.
In your Bible.
Yeah
So something to think about.
But yeah, so that is something that comes out of the work of Ezra, right?
Initially, these gathers and a sort of reorientation.
And the concept, we get the word Judaism from Yudeismos in Greek.
It's sort of a transliteration, right?
Right, and that's the word that comes in.
to being to describe the way of life, the way of being of the Judeans.
And so anyone in any city, even if you lived your whole life in Alexandria or Mesopotamia
or wherever, if you practiced Eudesmos, you were a Judean.
So Judean identity was not attached to living within the province of Judea.
And there were a lot of people who lived in the province of Judea who were not Judeans.
we're not considered Judeans, right? Right. Right. By the
Jews. This is what we might think of as a religious group, as
we would think of it now. Yes, this is where Judaism is born.
This is it. Yeah. The way we think about Judaism today,
right? This is this is where it is born. Now, obviously,
there's another big transition. And we've talked about this a
lot on the show between Second Temple Judaism, or
Judaism's.
By the time you get to the end of the Second Temple period and rabbinic Judaism, right? But
Yep, that is actually a smaller transition, believe it or not
Right because rabbinic Judaism really is kind of a continuation of pharisaism
That is less of a transition than the transition from
Ancient Israelite religion to Second Temple Judaism that is a much bigger transformation. Yeah
And we talked about this a little in the Mutatus Mutandus episode, too,
because this is in the Axial Age and all, right? Right.
So, yeah, so this is why Ezra is so important. And part of the reason why we really felt like
we needed to take this first half to emphasize the importance of Ezra and show how pivotal a
figure he is, is you might have the question
Why are there like 10 to 12 books claiming to be by Ezra of all people?
Right? Like you can understand people claim it was written by Moses, right? You can understand
people claiming it was written by, you know, Abraham or something, right? Or even Enoch, right?
But Ezra, well, Ezra, our, our, our contemporary understanding within a Protestant.
culture of Ezra is greatly diminished from the role Ezra was understood to have been
playing. Well, that it still really is in rabbinic Judaism and that it was historically in Christianity.
Ezra was this much more significant figure and we're going to see some of the results of that.
Alexander of this episode.
Exactly. All right. Well, on that cliffhanger, we're going to go ahead and take our first break and we'll be right back.
Father in
Father Stephen Daymack and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346, that's 855-A-F radio.
Ancient Near Eastern texts such as the Baal Cycle portray the pagan god Baal as a rebel.
The hero of a revolution worshiped and glorified.
for his long string of victories.
In the Baal book, A Biography of the Devil,
Father Stephen DeYoung shows that the Hebrew scriptures
consciously turn the Baal story on its head,
depicting him as a failed and defeated rebel
who nonetheless tries to steal the glory
that belongs to Almighty God.
From these scriptures, the figure of the devil
emerged within Jewish and Christian tradition.
Father Stephen works through the Old and New Testament passages
that refer to various Baal stories,
and he surveys Baal worship through followers' beliefs,
religious practices.
of liturgical life to show that the figures of Baal and the Devil, the Prince of Demons,
are one in the same.
You can find the Baal book at store.ancientfaith.com.
That's store.ancientfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damoc and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-234.
six. That's 855 AF radio. Hey, welcome back, everybody. It's the sixth anniversary of the
Lord of Spirits podcast to the day. We're six years old today. First grade. Does that mean
we get you're gonna have to learn how to read, Father Andrew? Stay up an extra half hour past
our previous bedtimes. No, I should not say that. I think you're all you are already
be passed, good hour passed.
your bedtime. What am I saying? Exactly. Exactly. Exactly. But
anyways, in celebration of our sixth anniversary, I'm reading
off some of my, maybe Father Stevens, who knows, favorite
reviews that we've received over the last six years of this
podcast. So you're ready for three more reviews, Father?
Sure. Okay, we do have a caller on the line, actually.
They may not be funny, but they're short.
That's true. They're short. Okay, so this first one is
titled
So here here's how it goes arrogance and ego along with foolish juvenile banter.
This was once a fascinating and lightning podcast no longer.
I'm unsubscribing one star one star.
See that what what makes that one interesting to me right
is not the and all that right.
Like I don't understand that like right off the jump it's that he was on board for some
a period of time.
fascinating. Like he was like, Oh, this is great. And then all of a sudden it all like
turned to dust and ashes in his mouth. I know. I'm wondering what episode and what I said,
because you know that's what it was. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. This next one, a little
contrast from the previous is titled delicious banter. Do you like the attitude era of
of WWE.
Do you love the Lord? Do you wish there was a way to make your level six paladin increases healing powers and become a war before the boss battle?
Do you love the british isles?
This podcast is it fam right?
question mark question mark
five stars
I don't know the reference the british isles actually fits i mean i do love the british isles
But i mean we don't they were trying to throw you a bone. That's clearly what it is
That's clearly what it is
Well, I see you that was banter and you were watching Attitude Era WWE.
I don't even I mean, I know it WWE is, but the rest of the I have no idea
when it what is the Attitude Era?
The Attitude Era is the late 90s.
OK, WWE, where they.
Started making edgy, we'll say edgier content.
That kind of got out of hand.
at a certain point and they pulled way back. The era after that is referred to as the ruthless
aggression era. You got to learn the names of different eras of wrestling. I can't back
that up. I don't know why you'd need to. But who comes up with these names? You could.
Well, ruthless aggression era has to do with a famous John Cena promo. But anyway,
okay. Yeah. All right. Here's a third. Are you aware of who John Cena is? Yes. Yes,
I'm aware. Okay. I won't go back.
that, but okay, so here's our third and final one for this
half. And this one's titled A Glass Case of Emotion. And here's
what the review says. When this all gets sorted out, LOS and I
should get an apartment together. Five stars. I feel like
that's a little forward. Yeah, I feel uncomfortable with that
one. Well, maybe the sorting out includes marriage.
So I mean, does the podcast have a separate marriageable life?
I mean, should we be getting a dowry or I don't know.
Yeah, I don't could it and another show become one podcast.
Yeah. Okay. All right.
We do have a caller is on the line.
So, uh, yeah, we've got Paul calling from Texas.
So Paul, welcome to the sixth anniversary of the Lord of
Spears podcast.
Hello, Father's.
Thank you for having me on again.
Yeah, yeah, welcome back.
back. I wanted to throw out a possibility as far as that first review that y'all read just
now. Maybe it was y'all talking about Samson that disenchanted them. It could be. It could
be. It could be. But I find a lot of those reviews where they feel like really betrayed.
It's something that I never would have thought. You know, like it's not one that
I knew was a spicy take. It's one that I thought was just like an off and remark
that would be uncontroversial.
But...
someone took deep offense.
That said, I do think that we should refer to the people
that are mad about the Samson thing as Sam Simps.
It's hard to pronounce slightly,
but I think it works, Sam Simps.
I don't know.
I'm not into all that alt-right jargon, so.
Okay, so what is truly on your mind, Paul,
from the great state of Texas?
It is indeed that.
So, and you all touched on it before,
into more depth about how the Sadducees and in particular the Pharisees actually attained their
authority. Because of course, you know, usurpation can happen, but the fact that it seems to have
been respected and acknowledged, and you know, y'all talk about the Pharisees authority and how
our bishops now have that because it was given to the apostles. How did the Pharisees attain,
let's say, the authority of Moses when they themselves are not like prophets in the old
school way like how how did that authority act?
actually make that transfer for them and for the Sadducees, you know, in their priestly
role.
Yeah.
I mean, we do have all the Hasmonean stuff that we did, but I mean, so give a short
trip from Ezra to the first century.
Well, so yeah, so the Sadducees, as we talked about in the Hasmonean episode, it was
kind of a hijacking, right?
They were not...
I mean, the sad...
When we're talking about the sad...
Sadducees were not really talking about like a religious denomination, we're talking about
just the high priestly families who control the temple.
And as we mentioned, Sadducee actually comes from the word meaning Zedekite, because the
sons of Zedek were supposed to hold the high priesthood in the Messianic age, and
they were claiming to be them even though they weren't.
That's why I say it was a hijacking.
essentially after their revolution, Judas Maccabeus made his brother the high priest.
And then later on, you have, like with John Hercannis, they're both the king and the high
priest at the same time.
So they weren't doing things correctly.
And that's why, well, that's one of several reasons why a lot of Jewish groups didn't
think the Second Temple was legitimate entirely.
involvement didn't help the fact.
that the glory of the Lord didn't return to the temple didn't help. There's lots of factors but
the Sadducees were one of them. So that was kind of a hijacking. And so their authority was really
just grounded in the fact that they literally controlled the temple and they had the authority
from the Romans because they were Roman collaborators to assess the temple tax and they
used that to enrich themselves greatly. So then being the wealthiest family in Jerusalem
that wasn't Roman gave them a lot of swing and they were in bed with the Romans who
who had the.
rest of the power. So the Pharisees had, we've talked before on the show about the Hebrew
words, mikah, that means like authority. And so if you read verses, Second Chronicles, that
is, we said earlier, traditionally written by Ezra himself. You see, there's tons of
genealogies. There's all this genealogical material.
even for like, you know, singers and musicians, right?
All of these different things.
And so the Pharisees had these elaborate succession lists
going back to Moses
that were how they said that they had the authority
to sit in Moses' seat, right?
we're on
All of the Tsumika chains that they offered as evidence completely airtight historically,
we can't possibly know, right?
I mean, there's no way to know at this point.
And there wasn't at that point either.
So were there probably people who were fudging a little bit, yes, right?
But that was in general, right?
They started with Moses laying hands on Joshua and they had a chain leading down
to them.
They really had a for-
normal ordination process during this period, that gets destroyed by the Romans in the first
century AD. So, as we said, I think in the ordination episode, or in the Apostolic Succession episode
maybe, one of those episodes, maybe both. In Jewish circles today, being ordained
a rabbi in a Jewish community now is not seen as being ordination in the same
sense as the the ordination of the second temple period. Yeah, because a rabbi is a teacher.
Yeah, because they acknowledge that those chains have been broken. Yeah. And there are
traditions that when the Messiah comes, he'll restore those. We of course, as Christians
believe that the Messiah came and did restore those by laying hands on his apostles and
than them laying hands on their successors
on down to today's vision.
Yeah. Yeah. So, all right. Well, hopefully that fills in the gap there for you, Paul. Thank you very much for calling this evening.
Thank you, Father's.
All right. Okay, we're going to roll on. So we're talking about Ezra's. I mean, there's so many Ezra's.
What's what's going on with all of that like where where all these books with that name come from I thought
it was just Ezra, Nehemiah. I mean, that was the those were the two books of the Bible
in that part of the Old Testament that I memorized back when I was a kid, when I could
name all the books. What's going on with all that? Maybe your greatest segue ever, I think.
Thank you. You're just going to the Jerry Seinfeld School of Segways now. Ezra, what's
up with that? What's up with Ezra? You guys seen Ezra? What's up with that? Thank
Thank you.
Yeah.
So, yeah.
So here's where things start getting messy.
And we're gonna take this half a little slow.
And if we're not taking it slow enough, call in.
Ask follow-up questions.
Actually, we got another caller that I want to take.
Oh, let's do it.
Yeah, yeah.
So we've got Kota calling from Utah.
So Kota, welcome to Laura's Spirit's podcast.
God, there's blood.
God bless you. Is this Koda Ibushi?
No
No, that's my I thought it would be weird if Koda Ibushi called it
My first question is the father Stephen if I have your book on my shelf does that mean that I have you I
Feel like you have a piece of me piece of my heart. Yeah piece of you. Okay
Well, so forgive me, I'm not the most knowledgeable I'm still
learning quite a lot. I'm actually a new Orthodox individual. But I had a question regarding
like the Divine Council framework. And so like, how does the return from exile fit within the
broader narrative of the nations being under the authority of spiritual powers? And what does
Cyrus being called God's anointed in Isaiah suggest about how God works through pagan
rulers within that cosmic framework.
All right, well,
That's straight to you, father. I think that's what's made for you. Yeah. Well, in terms of the second part, we have a whole episode talking about Cyrus. That is true.
Where we get into that in some some great detail. So but we can give you I can give you the short version now, but just if you want the long version like the three hour long version.
That's there. So that that is understanding that idea that the
um the Gentile nation
are under the authority of these evil powers is sort of crucial to understanding everything
going on here in that this is why they didn't see the return from exile as really being the return
from exile. Right? We tend to think about this in political terms as if like the Jewish people
were just upset that they weren't self-governing.
Right? Because we have all this democracy stuff in our head, right? Like, like, the Maccabean
revolt was not the American Revolution, right? This was not about self-determination and, you know,
you can't tax us without representation, right? It was the fact that they were under the power of
Persia, right? Think about Daniel, right? The Prince of Persia is this demonic entity that
that fights with the archangels, right?
meant that they were effectively under the power of evil still so yes they had
come back from Persia to that strip of land but they were still under the thumb
of Persia right and and Persia here again is seen as primarily in this
spiritual sense not in a materialist political sense
So the promise of return from exile, when you look at the prophetic passages that talk about
them coming back to the land and the restoration of not just Judah but Ephraim and the way the
whole Messianic Age is described in all of these things, that doesn't include, oh yeah,
by the way, demonic powers are still going to have control over the world you're living in.
Right. And so they're in this sort of liminal space, right, where they're kind of returned
from exile. Exiles kind of partially over in a way, but not really. And so having that
understanding of the evil spiritual powers at work is sort of key to understanding what
that and then how
Christ's defeat of those powers actually then does end the exile, right?
And that doesn't require anybody moving to the Levant.
Right?
Exile is not purely about what piece of land your house is on.
Right? It's a larger spiritual concept than that, as it was understood at the time.
time. And in terms of
of Cyrus, yes, he is the person who God chose to bring them back to the land, to restore
them, and to do everything. All those things we were describing Ezra doing for all of that
to happen. This is all within God's providence, but it's important to note like Saul was
also the Lord's anointed.
why David wouldn't kill him. That doesn't justify Saul's actions, right? That doesn't justify, that
doesn't mean Saul is a saint, right? And so God is the God of the whole world. He's the God of the
whole universe, right? Not just Israel, but, and so, you know, he works through who he
will.
Also.
did an episode where we talked about Nebuchadnezzar and everything that goes on between God and
Nebuchadnezzar and Daniel, right, on like literally like an interpersonal basis between
God and Nebuchadnezzar. So yeah, that's the, that's the short version of Cyrus. And
like I said, you can go to the long version in that other episode, which I don't remember
was, do you remember the title Father Andrew?
Not offhand, no.
sure it was a lever but 147th episode
out. So I used to know them all, but isn't there a spreadsheet out
there or something somewhere? Yeah, somewhere. Anyway, well,
thank you. Thank you very much for calling code. God bless you.
Thank you. Okay, now we will roll on. Yeah, so let's talk
about those books.
Them books.
What's up with them?
Um, so yeah, so
Oh, someone in the chat said that the name of the episode was protect the mule.
Oh, OK. There you go.
Yes. I thought that was the Nebuchadnezzar one.
No, I think, yeah, I think that might be right, actually.
That might be the Nebuchadnezzar one.
Um, yeah. Anyway, well, good, good, good.
The Cyrus one is the episode right after that, if it is the Nebuchadnezzar.
That seems right. That seems right.
Um, so, yeah, so, um,
and most
folks, I imagine, listening to us right now, are used to your standard English
Bible which has these two books in it called Ezra and Nehemiah. And you may
know, if you've studied this a little, that originally Ezra and Nehemiah were
always kept on
one scroll, meaning they were sort of seen as one book. And when you get the number of
books in the Hebrew canon from ancient sources, they talk about there being 22 or 24 books.
There's a bunch of things that are combined like the book of the 12 with the 12 minor prophets.
That was seen as one book instead of 12 books. Another example is Ezra and Nehemiah
that are now listed as two books in most English Bibles where one
We're one book together
What you may or may not be aware of is the fact that
There is another version
There's another competing book to that book
To Ezra Nehemiah as we'll call it with a hyphen in it, right? So there's Ezra Nehemiah
Which ends up being in the Hebrew canon?
We'll talk about why we're saying
it that way, ends up being in the Hebrew canon. And then there's this other book, usually referred
to as First Esdras, just to distinguish it, right, that is also referred to as the Book of Ezra.
In fact, it is what is more commonly referred to as the Book of Ezra in all ancient sources.
So, these two different texts, these...
two different competing book of Ezra's, right?
One is first Ezra's, one is Ezra Nehemiah.
Both of these begin with verbatim quoting
of the end of Second Chronicles.
And this is related to the understanding
that Ezra wrote Second Chronicles
because either version of the book of Ezra here,
begins with the end of the book of Chronicles. It's sort of like a classic
Doctor Who cliffhanger where the first two minutes of episode two are the last
two minutes of episode one. Just repeat it, right, and then it continues from
there. It is verbatim. So as we said, if you're used to an English Bible
Protestant Bible. You're used to seeing the canonical version being Ezra and Nehemiah, though now split into two bucks.
But there are weird things about that right off the bat.
One of them is that if you've ever read Ezra and then read Nehemiah, the two of them are different in a bunch of words.
ways. So for example, big swaths of Nehemiah are in the first person, i.e.
I, Nehemiah, in this year went and did this, right? Like it's written in the first person,
right, by Nehemiah. Whereas what's the book of Ezra in most English Bibles is entirely in the third person.
In fact, Ezra, this version of Ezra, right, that's in most English Bibles, reads pretty
much the same as Second Chronicles, right?
It's a third person historical narration, right?
Whereas Nehemiah has all this first person.
And that means there's sort of a genre difference between the two, even though they were both
of the same scroll, and we're being told we're treated as one book.
book. They don't seem like two halves of one book. They seem like two different texts that
have been just written together on the same scroll. And trying to come up with a theological
impact of accepting that version of the book of Ezra, Ezra Nehemiah as the actual book
of Ezra.
The most salient thing I could come up with is that Nehemiah, as we mentioned, is the
first governor of Judea, the Persian province, whereas Ezra is the religious leader, the
high priest.
Right?
And so by putting those two side by side, by paralleling them, maybe you're getting
at some kind of parallel but separation.
of spiritual and civic authority or something right but you may be wondering now why is why is
Father Stephen talking that way like accepting like that's the only version I've ever seen in any
Bible I've ever looked at well I have news for you right we said there's this other competing text
called First Esdras.
And 1st Esdras is just one text.
So we said Ezra Nehemiah really is these two separate texts written in different voices
and everything that have just been co-located under one scroll, whereas 1st Esdras is just
one continuous text.
It begins with the, uh,
last two chapters of Second Chronicles, verbatim as we said. So it's just word for word, the
last two chapters of Second Chronicles. Then it becomes, it has all of the material in it
that's in the book of Ezra in Ezra Nehemiah. So the English Ezra you used to reading, all
All of that material is there, but some of it's in a different order in first-estress.
And then there's a couple chapters of the book of Nehemiah
that happen to be a couple of chapters that are in the third person,
unlike the rest of the book of Nehemiah,
that are in first Esdras,
to make it one continuous narrative.
So you may be saying,
well okay, so this is like Daniel
where there's like a short version and a long version
that are like Esther where there's a short version of the long one.
version. Somebody took, you know, Ezra and Nehemiah and because it was messy, like you said, they sort
of smushed them together or worked them together. It's like a harmony of the Gospels or something.
They just they just worked the two of them together. Here's the problem with that idea.
Pretty much everybody in the ancient world
Jewish, up to a certain point in history, and then Christian, before the Reformation,
thought first Esdriss was canonical and Ezra Nehemiah wasn't.
And when I say that, I'm talking about, for example, Josephus.
If you read Josephus closely, the book of Ezra that he lists on his canon list is
is not Ezra Nehemiah.
He's specific.
says. He doesn't think Ezra Nehemiah is canonical, Josephus the Pharisee. It's
first Ezra's that he thinks is canonical. It's not just Josephus on the Jewish side.
Every church father, every single one that we still have extant today,
Right, we can discover new stuff tomorrow, but everyone that's accident today
Who comments on?
Ezra
Okay, that's not obviously not all church fathers ever comment on Ezra, right?
But all the ones we still have today who comment on Ezra
All hold first Ezra's to be the canonical one and not Ezra Nehemiah
So, yeah, Josephus and all of the, this shifts, this is one of the shifts and this doesn't get
talked about a lot because this kind of causes a problem for a lot of our Protestant friends
want to present the Protestant canon as this was the canon that was always accepted
by the juice.
not true. In fact they frequently quote Josephus ironically. Josephus the only
extra biblical author from the first century that tends to be kind of I mean
my grandmother had Josephus my Baptist grandmother had Josephus on herself. Right
but they quote Josephus to back up this guy this was always the Jewish
canon. But we know that there were changes. We know that the wisdom of
of Ben-Sirak was part of what became the Masoretic text until the late second century.
And we also know that Josephus, when he refers to the book of Ezra, is not referring to the
book of Ezra, Nehemiah is referring to 1st Esdras.
So Josephus is claiming that 1st Esdras was seen as canonical, always by the Jews.
And explicitly says he doesn't think Ezra, Nehemiah is canonical.
And the switch seems to have happened again in the late second century that the Ezra Nehemiah
takes the canonical place in the Hebrew text. Which means, and this is ground zero of this,
the Protestant Old Testament canon is not an Old Testament canon
held by any pr- in its exact de-
details, it is not an Old Testament canon held by any Jewish group before the second
century AD. Verifiably so, right? Like I said, this is ground zero of it. This is exhibit
day, right? So, yeah.
That's just sort of the case and and that that kind of
We'll get it as well. We'll get into that more in a minute
This does mean, you know, I'm gonna once again on ancient faiths airwaves be somewhat critical of the orthodox study Bible
The way they handle this is kind of weird
In that the orthodox study Bible has first second and third Ezra in it they kind of split the difference
They put in 1st Esdras, and then also put in Ezra Nihomaya, and just throw it all out
there.
And that's just not the historical testimony in terms of what's canonical.
So for the record, right, because we've like 1st Ezra, 2nd Ezra, 3rd Ezra, 4th Ezra,
right, how is this numbering?
working. Okay. Right. And first as dress second as dress. Right. So the way you get first through
fourth Ezra, and we'll talk about fifth and sixth later, but wait, it gets worse. So the way you get
to four Ezra's is you have first as dress that we've been calling first as dress, then Ezra as
Second Ezra right Ezra the way it appears
English Bibles as 2nd Ezra, Nehemiah as it appears in the English Bibles as 3rd Ezra.
And then a book that we're going to talk about in the third half for Ezra.
But if you look at, and see this is where the numbering thing comes in, if you look
at say the Latin Vulget, the Saint Jerome translated, Saint Jerome, he's one of those
churchwathers who come in on it.
translates first Esdras as the canonical book of Ezra, not Ezra Nehemiah.
And then labels what we now call 4th Ezra, he calls that 2nd Ezdras.
So he's skipping over the Ezra.
Yes, Ezra Nehemiah is not considered canonical.
So that's why in the Vulgate you have 1st and 2nd Ezras.
Yes, at 2nd Ezras he puts in his Deutero canonical section,
Fourth as right he puts the dude
cononical section but he puts it there with like Tobit and Judith and first and
second Maccabees stuff that is in the larger like Alexandria and Greek Canon
and stuff. So all that that I just said raises this question that you probably
weren't thinking you were gonna hear this evening. Is the book of Nehemiah
canonical?
What's canonical, Father Stephen? Yes. Yeah, we'll get into all that, I guess. But I mean, yeah, it's just, it's like, I mean, this, this is just underlines that what we, let me back up a little second.
What your average American Protestant thinks of as biblical canon is, is there's just that category just doesn't exist.
prior to other
16th century? Maybe before. I don't know. I don't think even it seems to be a Protestant invention.
Well, yeah, it's it's required by Sola Scriptura. Yeah. Yeah, right, right. Decide.
Once you play Sola Scriptura as a principle, right, and you and then you then make all
these predications about what scripture is and how it functions and what it does,
You have to then be very clear about
what is and isn't scripture. Yeah, which then like the problem then is that you it's really
hard if you look in the back end of that to establish where these texts come from, right?
Like, and the thing is, is that we're not just, you know, dunking on Protestants here.
There are Orthodox who act this way, but with just a difference of text, like I saw
someone just the other day basically say, you shouldn't say anything at all about
orthodox theology unless you can quote one
of the father saying the thing you want to say. And and also this the same person saying,
you know, basically that if it's in the church services, then they're dogmatic. That's dogmatic
everything. It's in the church service. But here's the thing. I know people who have
written hymns that get sung in church. Does that mean that that person was inventing
orthodox dogma when they I mean, I might have had a poetry, right? I myself, I myself
have helped to edit.
hymns to make them work better for Byzantine meter. Like I have
been called upon to do that work requested. Yes, exactly requested
by actual official Episcopal, you know, direction. Does that
mean that I'm creating dog in my hands, you know, that there's
human beings everywhere in this whole process. Yes. And and
There's not these sharp...
hard black and white lines around everything. There's just not. I mean, like you and I were
going over the differences between the Greek Orthodox, the Russian Orthodox, and the Georgian
Orthodox Old Testament canons earlier today, which are 99% the same. But, but not quite.
Not quite. And if you then if you add in the non-Calcedonians, which had their canons
basically in place if
before the schism of Calcedon, which meant that those were orthodox canons then, then it just
blows all of that to pieces. What does the church of the beginning of the fifth century look like
in terms of biblical canon? Well, there's probably at least seven or eight different canons in play
with the Old Testament. Well, and even the concept, again, even the concept, back of the
of the napkin. Right. All of the earliest, all of the earliest
Canon, Canon lists are are
inclusive, not exclusive. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Here's the stuff we read. So there's even there's
even issues with that, right? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. But this this just I mean, here's the
reality. Here's the reality. And this is well, first, let me say, because this is an anti
Catholic podcast, I have to take a shot at our Roman Catholic friends here. So some of
them have finally lit onto this fact that there are slight differences in the Old
Testaments used by different Orthodox
churches, and that this is some big dunk on the Orthodox church, which, guys, you didn't
have a single canon until Trent of the Old Testament.
You didn't.
Right?
There was one declared at Florence, and for 100 years before the Reformation, people
were publicly
debating it. Yeah. Within the Roman church. None of what we're going to kicked out of
for it. Okay. So that's not a dump, guys. Sorry. We don't believe in Sola Scriptura.
We don't construct doctrine from the Bible, right? So it's not an issue first. But yeah,
I mean, the reality is, the reality is, look,
to our Protestant friends.
There just kind of has to be an acknowledgement at a certain point
Okay, that
The arguments we the arguments we make to the argument orthodox arguments orthodox Christians make to
About the canon are all a posterior
Yeah, they're all after the fact. Okay, they're all post-hoc
They're all arguments that are made, you know, the reason the vast, vast, vast, vast, vast
majority of our Protestant friends have the canon of the Old Testament they have is that
from the first Bible that was handed to them as a kid to the present day, every Bible
they've ever looked at has had that Old Testament canon.
That's why they hold to it.
the, in other words, in other words.
the actual reason. Let's just let's just say it it's because it's Protestant tradition that
can you have because that's your group. That's the tradition in which you're located now after
the fact right you run it you encounter other people who have different views of the Old Testament
canon and so you construct arguments to defend yours over against those other views.
That's what I mean by after the fact. Yeah, right, but they are
the fact they're not the reason why no one walks into this world with a blank slate it's like I'm
going to read every text written in the ancient world and allow the ministry of the Holy Spirit to
tell me which of these are canon and which are not and lo and behold I've arrived at precisely
the fill in the blank canon of scripture that has never happened yeah there's never been a
a single case of that happening. Okay, right? We all receive what we receive.
And then after the fact, we try to understand it, right?
Maybe we fail to understand it
and so we change our belief, right?
We can't figure out a way to understand it.
Maybe it doesn't make sense to us at some point.
We change our belief or we find compelling reasons why,
yes, this is actually correct
and we use those as arguments,
but that's why people have received it, right?
So, you know, while it is.
while while me saying is the the book of Nehemiah canonical, right? Well, that is a little bit
of poke at our Protestant friends in that I don't know what of how a Protestant would argue that
the book of Nehemiah is canonical. If they actually know the facts, I don't know how they
would they would defend it. That doesn't mean no one can. Yeah, maybe someone has a good
argument about that. Maybe someone will hear this and do a response to it. I doubt it.
it. The only time people respond to clips of this show is to take
take them out of context and try to score points and get attention on social media.
But if someone actually were to try to understand what we're saying and wanted
to actually dig into it, the history of the book of Ezra, Nehemiah over against
first Ezra said all this and try and construct a Protestant argument for the
canonicity of Nehemiah. Cool.
I'd love to watch that on YouTube or listen to it on a podcast or whatever.
Right. Well, honestly, I would do it because,
because I don't know how you would do that.
So, hey, anybody listening who wants
to try and take a shot at that. Please do. Um, but right. Like it's, it's, it's, it's
not just a, uh, just taking a shot. Like I said, it's, it's, I honestly, I honestly don't
know how you would, how you would do it. Yeah. Right. And there may even be some orthodox
people now who are, uh, maybe somebody within the next week is going to go online
I'm going to be like, well, Stephen Young is denying the candidity of the book of Nehemiah.
I'm not denying the candidacy of anything, but we have to say some things, right?
Because as Father Andrew said, what does canonical mean?
If by canonical, you mean read publicly in the church?
Well, the book of Nehemiah has never read publicly in the church.
Yeah.
There are no Old Testament readings, right?
There are no church, like I said, all the church fathers we have,
we have what they refer to the book of Ezra are referring to First Ezra.
So, we don't have any Church Fathers to bring in to testify about Nehemiah, right?
There's a bunch of Orthodox biblical texts, Latin Vulgar, we already mentioned,
Slavonic Old Testament, right?
Don't have Ezra, Nehemiah, they have first Ezra's, and second Ezra's,
albeit in an appendix or off to the side, but we'll talk about that more in the third half, right?
So
So now as we said, there's a couple chapters of what is Nehemiah in English Bibles that
are part of 1st Esdras.
So those two chapters are canonical at least.
We can say that, right?
But the rest of it, I don't know, the only people, the only sources I can find that testify
to the canonicity of the parts of Nehemiah that are not in 1st Esdras are
rabbinic Jewish sources after the second century. I mean the reality is that no
matter who you are, no matter which religious tradition you're in, even if
you can try to do the whole soul scripture or a chapter verse thing, you
can't really even establish that without the life of your particular group.
Thank you.
Bye.
With an orthodoxy the life of the church is what it is. It's not reducible to even a, you know, macro set of texts, right?
It's not reducible even to the sum of all the church fathers and liturgical texts.
It's just not.
I hate to I actually had someone recently proposed the idea of trying to create an AI where they just dumped in every English
translation of a patristic text and make it so that you could quote unquote ask the
there's something I was like, that sounds like the worst idea ever. Yeah. Please, that's
a terrible idea. No. What would he even say? Whatever you wanted to hear. Yeah. Yeah. Right
exactly. Yeah. So yeah, here's another way to frame what we're saying here. Right. If
Again, you're someone who's actually trying to understand.
All right.
In terms of this case.
and this is the day of the book of Nehemiah.
Here's another way to take it, right?
And for our Protestant friends to take it, right?
In terms of just being a shot, right?
We've talked a lot on this show
about how in the Orthodox Church,
the edges of the Old Testament canon,
specifically the post-exilic texts, right?
Some of the ones we're talking about tonight
are at like the edge of the canon
and there's kind of a dotted line, right?
Around the edge of the writings, right?
There's the law, the prophet, the right, prophets, the writings.
right? Around the exact edges of the writings of the Old Testament.
And, you know, we've talked before about how in the West, before the Reformation, before Trent,
there were a variety of views. Basically, the North African view and the Western European view
were a little different, right? St. Jerome represents more of the Western European view,
St. Augustine represents more of the North African view within Latin Christianity.
And Protestants, right? We're now saying a Nehemiah against Exhibit A. Your old testament
cannon when you get in the post-exilic period is just as messy. Nehemiah is an issue for
you guys. It's not really super clean cut for you guys anyway. And the
reason, the only reason why it's a bigger problem for you than it is for the rest of
us is that that's holo-scriptura thing, which really needs it to not be messy. The rest
of us are in a position where we can tolerate some mess for various reasons. So then what's
the basic context, contents of the book.
of Ezra. As we mentioned, the return of the exiles, particularly the group that returns
with Ezra himself, the reformation of the community, the reformation of Judean identity
and what becomes Jewish known as Jewish identity centered around the Torah. And that takes
the form of the public reading of the Torah that begins with Ezra.
and they...
Understand the language that it's in right and that then becomes it. There's a language issue because they are reading the Torah as it has been preserved in Hebrew
Yeah, and most of the people do not understand Hebrew. They speak Aramaic now
Right burial Aramaic of the yeah, so which is like wait. I thought they were in the Persian Empire or you know
What's left of the Babylonian Empire?
Yeah, everyone's speaking Aramaic and this actually leads us into why
by people in 1st century Judea.
Palestine are speaking Aramaic. Yeah, believe it or not, everybody, Persian was not the
official language of the Persian Empire. Aramaic was. And how did that come to be? Well, it
actually comes basically down to the fact that there was a group of nomadic merchant
types who, by both traveling around and doing a lot of business throughout the
Persian Empire, but also getting kicked out of various places that they tried to
to settle by the
Persians and thus getting moved around, they made it
advantageous for everybody to want to learn their language
because that was the way that you did business. And so this
minority group, their language became the imperial language
basically because the, the imperial powers kept kicking
them around. It is one of the most amazing stories about
how a language becomes a lingua franca that this, this, you
know, abused minority group that their language comes to
dominate.
And I was just telling Father Stephen earlier when we talked about this that if anybody's
interested in that question, like how is it that some languages become kind of international,
how they sort of go viral? There is a magnificent book called Empires of the Word by Nicholas
Osler. And it's really quite a surprising set of stories, especially if you think that the
main way that languages are spread around the world is through violence. Actually, it's not
true, not not not true most of the time in fact.
and the Aramaic story is really, really a fascinating one.
So yeah, the official language of the Persian Empire
becomes the language that's being spoken in,
by Jesus and the apostles to each other
because of this history,
because of what we're talking about right here, yeah.
Yes, so the dialect of the Arameans.
Indeed, indeed.
Yes, so there's that issue that comes up,
but again,
This refocusing the public reading of the Torah and of the other scriptures, right?
Which is what's going to take place in the synagogues regularly right as a as a focus of
Community and religious life, right alongside the temple
Not instead yet, right when the temple goes away. It's going to be a stead, but
It's alongside at this point
and
then there is
Subituity with the crisis of interim
marriage. When Ezra arrives, he finds that some of the earlier waves of
returnees have intermarried with the local population without going through
the, having them go through the conversion process as outlined, for example,
in Deuteronomy. So these women are not becoming Jewish women.
They're not shaving their head and doing the whole thing. They're
maintaining their previous, what we would call ethnic identities, but
They're married too.
Hebrew men returning Judahite men. And so, again, this is part of that reframing of
Judean identity, right? Because for Judean identity to be resilient, right, looks what
happened to the Northern Kingdom. The Northern Kingdom, those tribes get deported to Assyria
and cease to exist because they intermarry with the local peoples.
So those tribes cease to exist, those identities within Israel cease to exist.
So for Judean identity to be resilient and to be resilient in Alexandria, Egypt and in Mesopotamia
and these places, there can't be intermarriage. Yeah. Right. Anyone who's getting married has to
become Judean, begin to follow Ude's most, right? So that that identity can be propagated.
generationally in places other than Judea itself, right?
And so this is, those two things that are the big crises
in first Esra's are the concrete example
what we were talking about at the end of the first half
about Esra forming what would become Jewish identity,
right, as a concept, right, as a thing,
You day is most.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, that's the second half of this episode about Ezra on the sixth anniversary of the Lord of
Spirits podcast. We're going to take another break and we'll be right back.
A royal life set aside, or a crown transformed into something brighter, Elizabeth, Princess,
Abbas Saint, a brand new children's picture book, invites readers into a world where kindness
sparkles brighter than jewels, and small acts of love ripple into eternity.
Walk beside a princess who chooses humility over splendor, finds joy in giving, and who
turns ordinary moments into something luminous reminding us that true
The beauty is not worn, but lived.
Elizabeth Princess Abbas Saint is available now
in our bookstore at store.ancientfaith.com.
Again, that is store.ancientfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damock
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-22.
two, three, four, six. That's eight, five, five, A F radio.
Hey, welcome back, everybody. It's the sixth anniversary of
the Laura Spears podcast, six years, 147 episodes. And
yeah, yeah, feeling a little nostalgic. So I have some
reviews suffering the pain over your memories of the past.
That's true. The dull ache. Well, in our in our dreams
episode. I think what your big thing at the end.
was like stop living in the past, Father Andrew, wasn't that essentially the...
If that's what you took from it, I think that's a valid takeaway.
That was my takeaway. That's my takeaway. Yeah, okay. I got some reviews, some reviews from
the past six years of the Laura Spears podcast. I have three more to share with us. So you're
ready for three more, Father? I don't know, but I mean, I figure it's going to happen anyway.
So right or not. Okay. Now this first one is titled talkies.
Theology, T-A-K-I-S.
You guys are like those Takis chip snack things.
Really good at first, questionable the next day,
spicy as heck, not quite sure I like you,
but painfully addicted.
Four stars.
I mean, I would have gone with Flamin' Hot Cheetos,
but...
Well, that's because you're a generation.
That's because you're a generation.
Exactly, exactly.
Takis are a gen Z.
as our Canadian friends would call it, a zoomer thing apparently. Okay, this next one has a,
I mean, the title is very unoriginal. We've seen this title many, many times. The title is Too
Much Giggling. So I thought it was going to be right, right? No, that's the other most popular
title for you. Yeah, this podcast is in the tradition of the sort of shock jock orthodox
theology pioneered by Schmem.
whom I respect, exaggerated by Hopko and now continuing with these two priests, it basically
boils down to forget everything you know about orthodoxy because it's wrong and probably Protestant
and let us illumined scholars enlighten you with what is really orthodoxy. It relies too heavily on
secular scholarship and analysis of the pagan religions of Israel's neighbors
and too little on actual Scripture, the gods of the nations or demons
and a patristic understanding of spiritual realities, two stars.
This is not one star
I've never heard father Alexander Schmabin characterized as a shock. Josh
Theology right because it's like father Alexander Schmabin Howard Stern. Who can tell the difference?
And and clearly father Thomas Hopko is basically the Alex Jones of
Yeah, I don't I miss at least yeah
Anyway
There's just a lot to love about that review. So much going on there.
OK, so here's here's the last one for our collection tonight.
And this one does not come from Apple's podcast.
So it has no star rating.
So this one, I think this one comes from Twitter as a record.
They just gave us no stars, no stars.
Just just put it that way. Yeah, just yeah.
This might be harsh, but the Lord of Spirits podcast is reckless
and should
be liquidated. Liquidated, Father Stephen. How much could you sell this podcast for?
I was going to say liquidated implies we have assets. That's right. You do. Well, I
think actually you have personal assets. They're not held corporately by the show.
That's right. That's right. They're not held corporately by show. I don't even have
personal assets. So I'm walking liability. Right. You live in total poverty, Father
Even
You know, well, technically, like if you take my student load debt into account, I do have
a negative personal network. There you are.
That's right. But but you just keep getting new degrees, father. So you can just keep
deferring the defer it right because you say, Oh, that's so sad now. Oh, it's so sad.
The father Stevens broke. Wait till I die without paying any of it off. I'll have
the last laugh. You could come after it from my Corpse City.
bank. Good luck. I feel like this should be noted on your
headstone in some manner. And I will see to it. So all right.
Happy anniversary, Father Stephen. All right, the third
out is the sixth anniversary in terms of material. Oh, I don't
know. Time in on the chat, everybody. What is the sixth
anniversary? It's not the paper. It's not. Are there any
Yeah, they would know.
this kind of thing. I think there are some I think we do have
some female listeners in the chat. I'm not sure. Someone did
just say in the chat that you are a negative asset to this
podcast. So there you go. Yeah, there you go. Yes, not zero.
dragging you all down with me. Exactly. One person says this
three halves business still makes me grind my tree teeth and
confused rage. Will someone else in the chat tell him why
we say that this show has three had it's amazing.
Just people, people are getting upset.
And it is a specific reference.
Someone let him know him or her.
I don't know which it is.
I think I'm starting to think our entire audience is hate
listeners.
I mean, I'm not against it.
I'm just starting.
I mean, yeah, welcome hate listeners.
We're very happy.
Yes.
No one actually unironically likes the show.
Yeah, right.
Right.
They feel compelled.
Yeah.
Do we have any calls?
Um
Yes, yes, we do have we do have a call. This person has actually a an on topic question,
and then he's hoping to sneak in an off topic one. We'll see what happens. Okay, so Ryan,
welcome to the Lord of Spears podcast. Oh, Father's bless. Can you hear me? God bless you.
Yeah, we hear you. Welcome. Welcome. You should actually do the off topic question
first. That way, we can't disconnect you before you ask it. All right.
go for it, Brian. You got permission from the ogre himself.
Awesome. So my question is about the oftenings. In your episode about the oftenings, you talk
about how Christ appears in the Old Testament and the way that the passages describe it
it's, is if he has some type of physical form or presence or there's a physical.
to how he appears. So my question is basically, is he, was Christ depictable or circumscribable
free incarnation? Because I understand the reasoning behind why we can depict Christ
and have icons of him is because of his human nature. So how does one understand
his form, his theophanic forms when it comes to detectable.
this in the Old Testament. Okay, well, depicticality. I don't know. Am I making
up words to pick just this? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Well, so this is one of the
interesting things, right? Because Moses comes to the people and says, you know,
when he's talking about idolatry, he says, I'm outside now, you saw no form.
Right? Therefore, you're not to play Scott in a form. But if you think
about it for a second.
Moses did see a form right yeah outside I yeah he spoke to God face-to-face but
Moses didn't make a depiction of the person he was speaking to he didn't even
make a verbal depiction hmm yeah like it like a description even didn't even do
the jack chick God thing
Yeah, like he didn't. Right. Same thing. So so Moses hypothetically could have because he had
actually seen a form. He had seen God. Abraham could have didn't. Right. So it's not a question
of couldn't. I think it's a question of didn't. Whereas we have depictions of Christ that go
go back to the time of the apostles.
Um, yeah, so there, there, there weren't like a ton of people who saw, there, there are a
handful right through the Old Testament at different times that none of them make depictions
of him.
Uh, likely I'm assuming because especially at that time, they were wrestling so hard
with the people's propensity toward idolatry, uh, because of the cultural norms at the
time.
Yep. All right. What's your on topic question, Ryan?
Okay. Yeah, thank you for humoring me on that one. I thought it was gonna be a wrestling or something, but
Maybe next time. Okay
My my on topic question is you're just talking about the the modern
Protestant definition of what can and means as opposed to
to the church fathers and how canon today kind of means this black and white
that in stone thing, but how exactly does the patristic era define or understand canon? I've
heard some people say that it's what's read in the liturgy and this they considered the 66 book
Canon canonical in the sense that it can be around the liturgy, but you all
said that books and I thought you said that certain books in the 66 book cannon aren't
read in the liturgy like Nehemiah. So how does the ancient patristic era define cannon if
they really do it all? Yeah, great question. So number one, for the orthodox anyways, there
are more than 66 books. At least, you know, however you divide them up, there are more,
Here is more text.
than the 66 books that Protestants use.
So there is not that I am ever aware of a place where the church fathers sit down and said,
and here is the canon of the New Testament, the canon of the Old Testament.
What you mostly get is church fathers say things like, as the scriptures say, and then they'll quote something.
Right? And then you also get
That's it.
For instance, there's the famous letter of, I think it's the year 367, the Paschal letter
of St. Athanasius, Father, which is the earliest known list of the 27 books of the New Testament.
And then he also lists books of the Old Testament, where St. Athanasius basically is writing
to his churches of the Church of Alexandria, this is after he's the Bishop of Alexandria,
the Pope of Alexandria, actually.
After he's the Pope of Alexandria,
saying,
these are the books that we read out loud in my churches. He does not say and this is like he
says nothing like the like you know the performers would say about you know biblical canon. He basically
says these are the ones that are read out loud in my churches and and then later and then you
also get like for instance the list of of St. Nickyphoros in the eighth ninth century
who's a patriarch of Constantinople?
where he says, these books are read out loud in church.
These are not, are read at home.
These are game set.
In other words, there are people arguing
about some of these books.
And these books are not to be read.
And so he's giving more complex picture
than St. Athanasius does.
And I think that there are other,
you can find other such texts like these.
But there's nothing that I'm aware of
in the church fathers that establishes
canon the way that the 16th century Protestant and Catholic
contemplation, you know, comments about this question go.
And so as a result then, the Orthodox notion of canon
exists within the living tradition of the church and is not a specific list,
is list that, you know, it's not like the creed, right, where everybody got together.
and it was officially ratified by the church fathers, here it is, word for word, you know,
we believe in one God, the Father Almighty, etc. It's just not like that. And as we mentioned
earlier, there are slight differences between the canons of the various Orthodox churches,
and there were even more differences prior to the 5th century. So, yeah, it's just
simply a much more complex picture.
Then you know a kind of like code of law that you can just look something up
You know
It just it just doesn't work that way the mentality is simply different and to me. That's not a bug. It's a feature
It means that that the life of the church is always alive in the church
And it's not this sort of dead letter that anyone can just sort of look up and have an answer
You know, it's within the church
and anything you want to
add or nuance or correct their father yeah well yeah so I mean all that is
basically correct the key thing is that there are these categories right there's
books publicly read books privately read books not to be read right that
everybody's putting things into so like the the Pascale Canon of of St.
Athanasius he's doing that in a deliberately exclusionary way he's
saying I don't want books other than these books to be read in my church.
because the Egyptian church throughout the 3rd century and into the beginning of the 4th century
was a mixed multitude to borrow a biblical term. There were Gnostics in what we would now call
canonical Orthodox churches. These clear boundaries hadn't been laid down. The reason we have the
Nag Hammadi library, like those texts, those Nag Hammadi texts, those Gnostic texts, is that
in the middle of the four states.
century when St. Athanasius started drawing these lines, they were buried by a monk in
the sand to preserve them, right? Because previous to that, most of these vodas were reading stuff
like the Gospel of Thomas and this other stuff, right? And so St. Athanasius had a
very particular intent with that, right? It now gets cited starting in the 16th century
those canonical debates, but what's
Athanasius was doing with it was something very different. You brought St. Nicoforus's
list while they're at it in the 9th century. St. Nicoforus says there in the 9th century
there were churches still in the 9th century that were publicly reading the Apocalypse
of St. Peter instead of the Apocalypse of St. John.
Which means that it was canonical in those churches at that time.
Yes. And they were fully in communion with all the other churches. Canon was never
the church felt like it had to divide over. Yeah. Yeah. Like the big old Ethiopian Canon,
the big old Coptic Canon, those were the cannons before Calcedon. That's not something that
happened after the split, right? That was always their cannon. And that cannon was
not an issue in the in the version the cannon was different the
Latin canon was not identical to the Greek or Slavonic collections, right?
That was, no one discussed that in the 11th century when Rome split, right?
So this was never seen as an issue that the church divided over, it was seen as there's
a collections of traditions, right?
And there are boundaries, there are those books not to be read, there are things
that are un-Christian, that are unsuitable to be read in.
in public worship. But beyond that, there was tolerance for a great degree of
variance within a certain field, right, of texts. And yeah, and the church fathers
were even more free than that. If you really start reading the church fathers
and you know what you're doing with ancient texts, you find wild stuff. Like
there are a couple sayings of the Gospel of Thomas that get quoted by
church fathers regularly.
as being authentic sayings of Christ. And for more on that. And sometimes the same
church father who condemns the Gospel of Thomas. Yeah. As a text. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I'll just
plug Father Stephen's book Apocrypha, which dives into all of this on a pretty granular
level at some in some cases yeah and yeah and we're going to talk about this half
We're going to be talking about 4th Ezra or 2nd Esdras in the Latin numbering, which
is sort of sometimes in your Bible, depending on what version you're reading, then how messy
it is at sort of the edge of the canon kind of as an example of this.
All right.
Well, thank you very much, Ryan, for calling.
And I hope that gives you something to chew on.
So all right, we're going to take one more call, and then we're going to roll on.
So we have Michael calling from the great Commonwealth of Pennsylvania.
Michael, welcome to the Lord of spirits podcast.
Hello, Father.
Have you rode the boat ashore?
No, no, unfortunately, no, no.
People keep telling you to, I know.
I should say that to my own local, Michael.
It's a good idea.
Yeah, anyway. What's up? Sorry. Sorry. Go ahead. No, you're fine. Yeah, I was just calling to ask is
I'm curious about the relationship between Ezra and the prophet Malachi.
I read a while back, and this was back when I was a Protestant, that Malachi's condemning,
like strong condemning of divorce was like him disputing with Ezra forcing the Jewish men
and to do.
their foreign wives. And I was wondering, you guys had any thoughts upon that?
Yes, is this an intraprophetic feud, as it were, Father Stephen?
Well, I mean, it is it is counter evidence toward thinking that
Ezra wrote both. That's the right. Right. Exactly.
But he changed his mind later. That's what it is. He changed his mind.
Yeah, well, so this is this is an
issue that was live in this post-exilic period, right? How this, how this situation is to be,
how this situation is to be handled, right? And we talked about how Ezra is founding later
Judaism. If you know anything about later Judaism, you know that it's basically just
a long string of historical arguments.
People arguing with each other, right?
But that's beyond, you know, the truth behind that caricature.
But beyond that, right, um, there's, there's lots of places
where the scriptures disagree with themselves, right?
Should you answer a fool according to his folly?
Parmer says both yes and no in different places, right?
And so there's, we have to understand that that's not there to be a contradiction, right?
It's not like, oh, hey, nobody ever noticed this.
Oops.
Those things are there because there was an understanding.
This isn't something that just comes out of postmodernism, right?
the idea that texts have to be applied.
The idea that a text by itself can't exercise authority. You could say a text is authoritative, but a text cannot exercise authority
It can't do anything. It's a text. It sits on a shelf. Yeah, right
right someone has to interpret and apply it
right and
Interpreting and applying the same principle
in different situations, even subtly different situations.
radically different applications, sometimes even applications that appear contradictory.
Right? And we see this all the time in the Orthodox Church. Does the Orthodox Church allow
second marriages? No, and? Yes. Right? Yeah. Does the Orthodox Church allow divorce clergy?
Does the Orthodox... I would just scandalize a bunch of people with this stuff because some
some people may not know about.
Things in the real world, but things happen all about the real world. Sometimes does it allow divorce clergy? No, but
Or what's while you run into one?
On and on and on right
Because there's there's sort of rules and principles and then there's real life and
Contrary to
the view of the Jewish tradition, even including the Old Testament that's been drilled into a lot
of our heads post Luther, the biblical Jewish tradition that we're talking about now, starting
with Ezra, right, was never legalistic. It was also always very grounded in the vicissitudes of
of real life. So I think what you're seeing is.
two prophets as it were speaking to similar but not identical situations and expressing
and applying the same principles therefore in different ways.
What unites them is that they have the same goal.
Their goal is the salvation of the people involved.
sometimes.
Sometimes that means you need to stay in a non-ideal situation and sometimes that means you have to leave a non-ideal situation
Yeah, yep
I got another question because like a
Because when Malachi speaks he's like the Seth the Lord and Ezra seems more like it's like a like a judicial thing like
You know like when the bishop, you know uses of the
Would they both be of an equal authority at that point?
Or like, how would that work out?
Well, so at this point, they're both in scripture,
so they're of equal authority, right?
But even in practice, even in practice,
it's another very popular thing we point out
here on the show, right?
The whole point, we talk about this
the Mosaic Succession episode, is that the profit, the role of the profit, starting with
Moses, was not just to repeat verbatim the words that God spoke to them, right? God didn't
need a human to do that.
The role of the prophet was to interact with.
the Lord, Word of the Lord, interact with Christ, interact with God, right? But then
to interpret and apply that to the people and to the situation they were in. And their application,
once they had pronounced it to the people, was binding, this is where the binding and
losing language in Scripture comes from, was binding upon the people to whom they proclaimed it.
So if you go to the Prophet say what do we do about the situation?
Right and the Prophet says here is what the Lord says it tells you what to do
You you got to do it you can't just be like oh, I'm gonna go ask another prophet get a second opinion
Right
So yeah, and then God God holds the Prophet accountable, but so there's there's not a significant
distinction there. And the fact that Malachi says, thus sayeth the Lord does not mean he
is quoting verbatim, something that was being whispered in his ear. He is speaking with the
authority given him by God.
Yep, yep.
Alrighty. Well, thanks very much for calling Michael. God bless you.
Okay. Fourth Ezra. Ezra. Ezra.
No, Fourth Ezra.
Sec.
Esdras. You're making this even more confusing for people.
I know. It's really like I've looked at all these these designations many many times now for years
and I I cannot cannot keep them straight. Yeah, just look it up in the Bible Father Stephen just
look it up in the Bible. Can't tell your Ezra's without a program.
time. So yes, so 4th Ezra and 2nd Ezdras are the same book as we said before.
with the numbering, right? If you're counting Ezra's and you're including
first Ezra's and Ezra and Nehemiah, then this is fourth Ezra. If you're just
going with what is the more ancient Christian tradition, you follow St. Jerome
and you have first Ezra's, which is the canonical book of Ezra, and then
second Ezra's is this text. And Ezra Nehemiah, the Hebrew Ezra Nehemiah,
is not included.
So that's why you get the two number X. So this taxed forth Ezra is
semi canonical
hmm
Okay, any orthodox church actually got it in their cannon for whatever sort of for whatever however one would define that word
Yeah, like what happens. Yeah, actually, it's funny. We were we were looking earlier today
We were trying to figure out which orthodox churches have various books in their Old Testament Canon
And we decided to look something up in the Russian, the Russian Synodal Bible.
But that's not exactly the canon of the Russian Orthodox Church, even, right?
Like it's right.
It is a translation.
And by the way, actually, there's an Orthodox edition and a non-Orthodox edition of the
Russian Synodal Bible.
Yeah.
Which is not, is it?
But here's the fun thing, everybody, is that the majority, not all of it, but
the majority of the Old Testament of the Russian Synodal Bible.
Are you ready for this, everybody?
special.
you kids that came became orthodox in the 90s because of certain kind of apologetics being done
those days. The Russian Snowdeau Bible significant most of the Old Testament was taken from the
Masoretic text. Yeah, not from this anything called the substitution. You know why? Because
they've got it. They have it. Yes, Lenin grad is Lenin grad is for that letting grad like it's
in St. Petersburg. They have it. They have the Masoretic text. The Masoretic text is an
and orthodox.
Bible. The Orthodox have it. It's not an Orthodox Bible, but
the Orthodox have it. Yes, I don't know. I mean, it's just it
was never read. The Hebrew was never of that book was never
sure. Okay, surgically in an Orthodox church. Right. But
so it's not an Orthodox Bible in that sense. But even then,
like the the the Russian Synodal Bible is not of course,
because in Russia, they're worshiping in Church Slavonic.
Right. Maybe they didn't just translate the church. They
It did not just translate this level.
Bible into modern Russian, interestingly. Yeah, yeah, they did their own new
translation from the Masoretic text and in Greek text as well. Yeah. I don't know,
it's just a wild, wild world out there when you're talking Orthodox Bibles kids.
It's just really interesting. I love it. I love it. Yeah, yeah. So, so for example,
if you're reading St. Jerome's Latin Vulget, as we said, it is
with the books that he considered deuterocanonical.
And let me say this, let me say this too.
I didn't say with the collar.
There's a hierarchy of authority among books in the Bible.
Yeah, yeah, within the books that are read publicly.
There's a hierarchy of authority.
Right.
I mean, in the Old Testament, it's obvious.
It's obvious reading the
New Testament, that the Torah was of a unique and different kind of authority than the prophets
and the Psalms, which are of a greater level of authority than the stuff that's in the
writings.
Right.
That's part of the reason why the exact contents of the writings and different versions of
books was so, was allowed for in the writings is they were exercising a lower level of
authority.
So it wasn't as important that we be right.
is the Torah super strict in terms of...
of copying and everything. And in the New Testament, if you've been to an Orthodox liturgy,
there's a reason why we stand for the Gospel reading, and the Gospel reading is only done
by clergy, while the Epistle reading could be done by pretty much anybody, even a non-Orthodox
person.
You're gonna scandalize everyone again, Father Stephen.
Yeah.
and people sit during it so there's even these levels of authority within what
is canonical right if you don't understand that then you you're not gonna
be able to understand the concept of something being canonical but not at the
same level as other canonical texts which means you won't understand what
Saint Jerome is doing right Saint Jerome has this section
of Old Testament books that includes stuff like Tobit and Judith and 1st and 2nd Maccabees
and 2nd Esdras and 4th Ezra. Protestant apologists try to leverage this to say,
oh, see St. Jerome didn't think those books were canonical. It's like, well, yeah, he did. He
just thought canonical authority was on a sliding scale. He didn't have the idea of
of Sola Scriptura so he didn't have this one zero.
idea of canonicity, right? He saw relative authority within these texts, right? Because
there are plenty of other texts that Saint Jerome did not include in that section, like
First Enic.
Right. Deuterocanonical means second canon. It doesn't mean not canon.
Yes. Right. Like, he didn't put First Enic in that section.
Yeah.
But he also didn't put the books in that section with the other Old Testament books,
he saw it different.
on both sides with those books, right? He thought it was more authoritative than
some books, but less than others. And it is also, 2nd Esdras, 4th Ezra, is in an
appendix to the Slavonic Bible. What does that mean?
to get inflamed and potentially kill you unless removed. No, it's, right? It means it's, it's
in there, right? There's a lot of other books that aren't in there. Again, First Enoch is
not anywhere in the Slavonic Bible, right? Or Second Enoch, even though we have it in
Slavonic, right? So it's more authoritative than those, but it's in an appendix. That
means it's less authoritative.
that other Old Testament books in the Slavonic Bible. So based on that, as you
might imagine, at least part of 4th Ezra was originally written in Hebrew.
There's part of it that was very obviously originally in Hebrew is what
that means. So there are some scholars take the position it was all
all originally in Hebrew.
other ones say, well, those parts were in Hebrew and other parts were in Aramaic or whatever, right?
There's a lot of back and forth, right? And we're also pretty sure that there was a Greek version at
some point because Saint Jerome translated it, but he said one of the reasons he put certain
books into that Deutero canonical category is that they weren't extant in Hebrew, right? And
And he did translate 2nd Esdras.
So that implies if he didn't have the Hebrew copy, he had a Greek copy and that's what he was translating from into Latin, right?
But today we don't have any Greek or Hebrew versions. Extent.
No copies. So we have 4th Ezra in Latin from St. Jerome's Vulgar, in
in Slavonic from that appendix of the Slavonic Bible and in Ethiopic because as we all know the Ethiopian
Opian Bible has everything in it, including 4th Ezra. So this text, as we mentioned,
1st Ezra was usually referred to by the Fathers as the Book of Ezra, and by Josephus as the Book of
Ezra. Whereas 4th Ezra or 2nd Ezra is referred to by them usually as the Prophecy of Ezra,
to distinguish the two book of Ezra prophecy of Ezra
It was interestingly, as far as we can tell, written around the end of the first century AD.
Wait.
Yes, it was written around the time that the book of Revelation was being written.
Okay.
So is this a New Testament book, or...?
This is one of those interesting things, the book of wisdom, the earliest canon lists we
have listed as part of the New Testament, not the Old Testament.
Hmm.
It's a lot of interesting things.
We don't have anybody listing forth Ezra as part of the New Testament.
It's pretty much written around the end of the first century AD.
And, and...
We're going to get into it when we get into some details here was written by a non-Christian Jewish person.
What? Because our Latin version has been Christianized.
It's been added to it's been edited to make it more on the nose Christian, at least.
So, yeah, but the fathers cite it frequently in an authoritative way.
Yeah this text
St. Ambrose in particular cites it all the time
so he seems to have just
Found it especially helpful, but the most interesting citation of
4th Ezra historically to my mind
Goes from Christopher Columbus. You didn't think he was gonna come up today
This is so wild. Yes. So, Christopher Columbus, hero of Italian people everywhere. And when
he was trying to sell the Portuguese on financing his, his expedition, right? He, he
quoted to them, second Esdras, two verse six. Second Esdras, but this tells you, so we're
talking about the 15th century now. So second Esdras, even though it's in this Deuteronical
status and stuff in the Latin and everything is still super well known all through the
medieval period, right? In the West in the in the Latin, right? And I'll be
Obviously, in Eastern Europe and the Slavonic, we're talking about mostly 2nd millennium Christianity.
Christopher Columbus quotes it as, it indicates that the Earth is 7 8th land and 1 8th water.
The Christopher Club has did the math.
Based on that
Yeah, I just think about that for a second
It's not only are they familiar with second estrus
This at best Deutero canonical book
But they think it is accurately describing the Constitution of the planet Earth
Enemies using it for a loan application. Yes, literally betting his life on
it yeah yeah his life and his fortunes and the lives of his crew on this being
accurate and gives the estimate from remembering the number right that Japan
was about 2400 miles from Portugal pretty sure that's not true no matter which
direction you you go no there's also another continent in between yes it's
It's actually like 6,300.
You have to fly to get there is the crow flies because yeah, North America, but that's how confident he was that second answers was correct at the end of the 15th century.
15th century. Yeah, so as we as we mentioned ago, the Latin version has these editions.
And there's additions at the beginning and additions at the end, both of which have been divided into two chapters.
So it ends up being the first two chapters and the last two chapters of the Latin version of 2nd Ezra.
These are an obvious Christian addition because they're like super on the nose as in like they're basically taking the rest of the text and being like, see Jesus fulfilled this.
Hmm. Yeah. Right. Like.
This was obviously was fulfilled when Christ did this XYZ, right?
So yeah, those are obvious. Obviously. Those are Christians, right?
We're writing that the Slavonic version and the Ethiopian version don't have
those opening or closing chapters. Hmm. It's just in the lat
And so get ready for this just what you thought you kind of had a handle on this
Those first two chapters at the beginning that are added are referred to as 5th Ezra.
So 5th Ezra comes before most of 4th Ezra slash 2nd Ezra.
Yes.
Got it?
4th?
And then the last two chapters that were added onto the end are referred to as 6th
Ezra.
So you got 5 and then 4 slash 2 and then 6 if you're reading the Latin version, yes.
Thank you for your patience.
They're supposed to be so orderly, orderly, you know, right?
And come on, codify guys, that's that's so precise.
And yet here we are, right, like.
OK, so I see.
So you now know the identities of first through sixth Ezra.
We're not done, but back to fourth Ezra.
OK, so a note on a major figure.
in
4th Ezra who's also major figure in a lot of other second temple Jewish literature
and
That is St. Uriel the Archangel Uriel. Yeah, he's the fire one, right?
He's the fire. Isn't that what or is fire? Yeah, the fire of God
I was one of the seven archangels I've met a couple orthodox Christians named Uriel, so I mean that's pretty cool. Yeah
Um, yeah.
So I mean, of course, Archangels, Michael and Gabriel, President and everybody's Bible,
Saint Raphael is in the book of Tobit, right?
This is the most canonical book that the Archangel Uriel is named in, but he's also, he's on
the lists.
You get these lists of the seven archangels and those four are pretty much the same on
all of them.
Right.
and the other three
go different ways, depending on what you're reading. Yeah. So, but
Uriel traditions about Uriel, these aren't all these are not in
fourth Ezra. We're going to talk about him in fourth Ezra here in a
minute. But just to give you an idea, right, that it's not
just Oh, this is a character in fourth Ezra. Like this is say
here is a figure, right? Who appears in a lot of this
literature. He is traditionally the
Angel who rescued St. John the Forerunner and his mother St. Elizabeth from Herod's men
and led them to flee into the desert. If you want more on that, we did a St. John the Forerunner
episode where we talked about that more. A lot of our contemporary Christian folks
don't know about that whole tradition, right? St. John was born not that long before Jesus.
So, when Herod went to kill everybody under the age of two, they came for St. John also,
and that's when St. Zacharias was killed, St. Elizabeth fled with St. John into the wilderness,
St. Elizabeth then passed away and St. John was raised in the wilderness by angels.
This is Christian tradition from as early as we can find, right?
But we talk more about that in that episode, but you can see this in terms of the
Archangel Uriel.
If you look at Leonardo da Vinci's The Virgin of the Rocks, you will see an angel there.
That is Uriel, there with St. John and St. Elizabeth.
He is also the angel who accompanied the Holy Family on the flight into Egypt and you can
find him in
sort of the earliest written text that we have that includes that tradition is
Pseudomathia, but if you take a look at Coptic and other Egyptian liturgics and
early sources, it's all over the place about Uriel being that angel. Yeah. He's
He's also in the Apocalypse of St. Peter that we mentioned earlier.
I thought we had done an episode about it with Father Edward. I were talking earlier,
but apparently we haven't. So we look out for that in the future. Yeah, because the Apocalypse of
St. Peter is a super important text. Early Christian text, but Uriel is there. And there's the
Angel of Judgment and both St. Dionysius, the Ariappa guy, when he lists the seven
archangels and Saint Gregory the Deologist when he lists the seven archangels have
Uriel prominently featured. So this isn't just an angel who shows up in
4th Ezra. This is an angel that's known from all kinds of other traditions and
other texts who is also in 4th Ezra. And in 4th Ezra, so 4th Ezra proper, if you
take off those first two chapters and last two chapters, is made up of 12
Those 12 chapters describe seven visions that Ezra has.
And Uriel, over the course of these seven visions, is acting as the sort of guide, as the psychopomp, as it were.
And so the first three visions are actually in the format of Ezra asking God questions.
And they're not like abstract questions.
like is that like
Why is the sky blue, right?
Like it's not just sort of like, I've always wondered,
why do birds sing so sweet?
Why do they?
Anyway, it's, he's questioning God, think more Job,
right at the end of the book of Job.
And this is, this becomes a theme
surrounding the figure of Ezra.
We'll talk about that more in a little bit,
but it's expressed here.
in the first three visions. And really, it's not really three separate questions. It's sort of one
broad question. And then the second two questions are kind of drilling down on parts of the first
question. Right. So the first question is, he's questioning God's justice because of the
continuation of the Exile, right? Like we were talking about with the collar.
Ezra is aware that yeah, okay, we're back in the land, but we're still ruled over by the Persians and the forces that rule the Persians and
Right, this isn't really the restoration that was promised, right by through the prophets
At the end of the exile, right and
Then the second question like we say is kind of drilling down why was why was Judah forced into exile in the first place
And then the third question is why is this pagan empire?
Why is one of the pagan nations ruled
by these evil powers in charge?
Right, you can see how those second two questions
are just drilling down on the first question.
Yeah, yeah. In different ways.
And the basic answer, right,
I mean, we're not going through verse by verse here,
but the basic answer that God gives us twofold.
Number one is the answer that he
He kind of gives Job at the end of the book of Job, which is, you know, God has his counsels.
He has his ways. He has his plan. He has what he is doing. And you small human couldn't
understand it if he tried to explain it to you, right?
Who art thou, old man, et cetera? Yes. So there's that element. But then there's
also God's promise of judgment. As we've talked about on the show before, remember
Justice is everything being
the correct place functioning properly. And so God is saying, no, that is coming. You
may have been expecting it as soon as you got back onto Judean soil, but it is coming.
Everything will be set right. The wicked will be put in their place. The righteous
will be exalted to their place. Justice will be established once and for all. That
day is coming.
And so that's judgment as a promise to a suffering people.
So then the fourth vision is one that we've talked about on the show before.
We verified this.
The fourth vision is usually called the vision of the bridegroom.
And so we did an episode called One Flash where it was in our sacrament series.
Our series on the mysteries of the church where we talked about marriage.
appropriately enough since this is the bridegroom vision. So you can go back and listen to that
episode, we drill down a little more on, I need to stop using drill down, we focus it a little
more and go through in more detail this particular vision, the fourth vision of Ezra here in
fourth Ezra. And, but basically in broad strokes, the vision is that this bridegroom,
he comes to the threshold of the bridal chamber going in with his new bride to
consummate the marriage.
and he drops dead on the threshold. And then within the context of the vision
he's mourned by his mother and then his mother in this mourning process is
transformed and becomes a city, specifically the city of Zion, like
Jerusalem, like the heavenly Jerusalem. Now that may just seem weird. Stop your
But I would refer to
you, and we talk about this in the episode we mentioned so you can go there, but I would refer
you to a lot of our pascal liturgics, a lot of the things we sing about the Theotokos,
who is Christ's mother, the bridegroom, who died at the threshold of the bridal chamber,
and how we switch from talking about her, the Theotokos, Christ's mother, as this person,
and start talking about her as a city and the city of Zion.
So, this imagery, right, of the bridegroom, see that episode from where it gets incorporated
into our hymnography around Holy Week, right, Bridegroom Mountains, Holy Week and Posca.
The fifth vision is often called the Eagle vision.
You'll never guess why, because there's an eagle in the vision.
What?
Crazy.
But I've just
any eagle says a bald eagle representing America. It is a three headed eagle. Ah, who has two
sets of wings. One set of 12 wings and one set of eight wings. I hope they're evenly distributed
so that's like 10 on the side. But yes, I think it's six on one side and then four
on that side and then six and four on the other. Okay, okay, because I was like 12 on
on one side, A will be.
Anyway, so the in the text of the vision, it identifies this eagle creature with the fourth beast, the fourth kingdom, the fourth kingdom of Daniel's prophecy.
So that would be the fourth beast.
That would be the the iron in the statue, the succession of empires, meaning Rome, right?
this is an image of Rome, and not just of Rome in general.
So once the text identified, as you're thinking about Rome,
when you look at the particulars of the three-headed eagle
and the 12 of the eight wings,
this is particular iconography that was used
by the Flavian dynasty at the end of the first century,
specifically around the time of the emperor Demetian,
meaning that this is referred
to the exact same time period as the revelation of Saint John. So this is kind of overlapping imagery
with his beast imagery. Now what happens in the Eagle vision is as this eagle representing the
Roman Empire, there's a lion, the lion of the tribe of Judah, i.e. the Messiah, and according
to the text, and this is how it is expressed in the text, the lion kills the eagle
and then burns it alive. I know you're thinking in that order. Yes. How can you burn it alive
if you've already killed it? I don't know, but it's how it is. Yes, it's just next level.
And relatedly, in the 6th Division, Ezra sees the Messiah get attacked by this big
mob of people. And so he sets them on fire. Oh, there's a lot of part of the reason for this fire
motif is Uriel, right? Yeah. Okay. Okay. And judgment, right. So he sets them on fire, and then he goes
and he finds new disciples elsewhere from other people. Because they didn't like him. Now, the
Christian interpretation of that is probably super obvious to you. Sure. Yeah. Right. Kingdom
be taken from you and given.
to the Gentiles. Those who produce the fruit thereof, yeah. And so then the seventh vision,
this seventh vision is actually the, if somebody knows a little something about Fourth Ezra,
this is probably the vision they know about, because this has to do with the restoration
of the scriptures. Yeah, someone was asking about this in the chat earlier about Ezra and the
Torah yeah so there is a tradition floating around
in the first century AD, we have a bunch of examples of it.
Not just here in 4th Ezra, but the Epistle of Barnabas is an example of it
that holds that at some point in the history of Israel, the Torah was lost.
Yeah.
Like the literal text was destroyed and they didn't have it anymore.
In the case of 4th Ezra, this happens at the time of the Babylonian conquest.
So at the beginning of the exile, when they burned the temple.
they burn everything. They burn all the copies of the Torah and all the other scriptures.
All get burnt, destroyed, the Psalms, everything. They lose them all. And within Fourth Ezra, then
in the Seventh Vision, the Seventh Vision is really sort of a trance that Ezra goes into.
And it's described that way. He sort of goes into this trance and then he wakes up and he
he sort of finds these books that he's written and he reproduces the 24 books.
the scriptures word for word exactly to what they were before the exile. So he
restores them. So I wrote a journal article about this at one point. You can
track it down online if you look for it. Because talking about this tradition
specifically because Saint Jerome refers to it.
In his
St. Jerome a lot of people don't know this he wrote prefaces to the different parts of his biblical translation
like introductions
So he has an introduction to his translation of the penitouk. It's kind of like a
Proto study Bible on some level. Yeah
Where he talks about linguistic issues and things and whatever else right and introduces the text
That's where some of these notes about who wrote what?
where he has these kind of sometimes odd ideas about who wrote a particular book.
That's where you find that stuff a lot of the time is in his prophecies.
So in his preface to the Pentateuch, he's talking about some of the language of until
this very day that you find in the Pentateuch. And basically, he makes this offhand comment,
whether you think Moses wrote it or whether you think
I think Ezra was the Latin Instaurator.
of it. It doesn't matter either way, right? So he's saying whether you think until this
very day is Moses day or until this very day is Ezra's day, it doesn't really make a difference.
That's the point Saint Jerome is making in context. Okay. That's not the interesting part.
The interesting part or the reason why someone would write a journal article about it is that
starting with our 19th century German friends. So remember the the playbook
The playbook of more quote-unquote liberal biblical scholarship of the 18th, especially 19th and early 20th centuries was we have to date every book of the Bible as late as we possibly can to give us maximum flexibility in terms of it not being historical at all.
And so, one of those things was, there were a lot of folks wanting to make the Torah, the
whole Torah, post-exilic.
It was just written after the exile, right?
And so, or subversion of that, right?
Like Deuteronomy was written by Josiah, right, that kind of thing.
We're trying to push it late.
And so, this quote, by saying...
Jerome was taken out of context and sloppily translated to say, Oh,
Saint Jerome doubted whether Moses wrote the Torah. Yeah. Right.
He thought Ezra may have written it after the exile to try and say, Oh, look,
here's a here's a famous saint and church father who had this modern idea.
Right, to try and give some end.
antiquity and prestige to it. And to the credit of their guile, they were so successful that
you could pick up quote-unquote conservative traditional, like evangelical Protestant
conservative books on this in biblical studies. And they will say, they will just repeat
the idea that Saint Jerome questioned whether Moses or Ezra wrote the Torah.
Wow.
This has just become this common nugget.
This is what caused me to write the journal article.
Right?
It's memes.
I saw that.
Memes for centuries.
Yeah, I saw that in a relatively conservative,
protestant source and I was like, really?
He did?
That struck me as odd.
And so I actually looked it up
and I looked it up in the Latin and stuff, right?
That's how I know the word was insturator.
And that's what I discovered that that's not at all what he said, right?
It's Serato, or basically is a word for it, what we would call an editor, but it
refers not to, it can refer to not just to somebody who edits a work, but
somebody who restore, edits it in terms of restoring it, correcting it, right?
Re-establish it, making a new, a new, better, clean copy of it, right?
And so...
And once you know that St. Jerome had translated 2nd Esdras this passage, right, and that this
was a tradition going around at the time, he's referring to this tradition. He's saying,
whether you think the text as we have it comes directly from Moses, or you think that
Ezra restored it after it was lost, but restored it word for word for what it was before the
the exile.
it doesn't matter, right?
I say that not to plug my journal article,
but just because I think this is a good example,
this is a really good example
of how even when you're reading orthodox sources,
because I've had this happen more than one time,
I'm not gonna name names,
but where an orthodox academic or scholar
will offhandedly say, this church father says blank,
and it strikes me as weird,
But I go and I look it up.
the original language and that's not what they said. Yeah. So don't just take for granted,
even if you see it all over the place, even if it's become commonplace like this has, don't
just assume that that means it's true. Yeah, because a lot of people just repeat and repeat
and repeat and repeat. Right. They've heard it and they repeat it. Right. So the text
I was reading was not a lit that I saw this in about Saint Jerome was not like a liberal
tax tried to late date the
The Torah that wasn't in their agenda at all, but they had just taken this on as being a fact
Yeah, and never checked
Right. Yeah
So yeah, do that do that all the time
Right something sounds fishy to you
Go check
So
The other interesting thing here about this seventh vision in the Restoration of the text he restores the 24 books
But then we're told and this is the way it's usually translated
He also
restored
The 70s secret books
Secret books, this is good stuff finally revealed the secret books of orthodoxy. Yes the 70s secret books of Ezra
So here's here's the thing so people will try to jump
Oh, clearly, 4th Ezra was written by a Jewish sect which had a collection of 70 sectarian
texts that they were attributing to Ezra.
Yes.
But here's the thing, we know of no such group.
We know of no group that claimed to have 70 books like this.
No one has any evidence of any candidates for what any one of those 70 books might
even be.
Okay, and
Right, you could also
Translate 70 secret books here
You just translated a little differently
can also say
The apocryphal book of the 70. Oh
You mean it just means the subtergent
Most likely yes, that's actually what he's talking about
about. And so, yes, and this reflects, the idea is then that this reflects the end of
the first century AD, the special place that the Greek translation still occupied within
Jewish life, as opposed to the Aramaic Targums and other translations. So there you go.
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. And you may be wondering, wait, how could he have written it? How could the
historical Ezra have written it in Greek? Well, number one, this is the end of the first
century. But number two, remember, he did it in a trance.
There you go. I mean, I can write in Greek in a trance from in the right trance.
Yeah, right. Like trance music.
He doesn't have to know the language to produce an entrance.
And also, why are you asking questions like that?
Do you not understand the genre we're reading?
Right, it's Apocalypse, you guys.
OK, so we've now gone through six Ezras.
You may think, surely there can't be more than six Ezras.
Oh no, we have four more.
What's better than six Ezras?
10.
Better than Ezras.
So the next one we're going to talk about
the Greek Apocalypse of Ezra.
Also written in trance. I don't know. I'm just throwing that out. No, probably not
Although we don't know because in terms of when was it written the answer is who knows
Yeah, so we have it fragmentary
The latest estimate because you know when our manuscript is from is that it was written in the 9th century
But there are scholars who argue that it was
written in the second century.
And scholars who argue is written everywhere in between
because journal articles have to be published
and dissertations have to be written.
And so if you've got an unknown like this,
here you go, put forth your argument
for the provenance of the Greek Apocalypse of Ezra.
And it's kind of fragmentary, which doesn't help, right?
In terms of trying to date something
and figure out the context.
But journal articles have to be written,
dissertation. Yeah, every public.
So it is the Greek Apocalypse of Ezra is explicitly a Christian text like it mentioned St. Paul and
St. John by name. Okay. Like it doesn't vaguely allude to St. Paul. It talks about St. Paul,
right? So this is very clearly a Christian text. Interestingly, you know, we've talked about
these texts that list the seven archangels. It lists nine.
I don't know. I mean one of two uppers. I don't know. Yeah, why not?
And what are their names? Yeah, the extra names are fascinating. They're awesome
And I strongly suggest someone name their children at least one of these
I don't think any of them are saints in the Orthodox church though. Really? Okay. Yeah
I've never seen them available to you cynics. So the first four are the ones you'd expect
Yeah, Michael Gabriel Raphael and Yuri Uriel. Yeah, yeah, right
But then Gabu Thelen, Gabu, Gabu Thelen, Gabby for short.
Acre, Acre.
OK, that's easy.
Our Fugotonos.
That's my favorite, actually, of these,
although Gabu Thelen is pretty close second.
Our Fugotonos.
Our Fugotonos with a P.H.
With a yeah, I point out because I can identify.
I've had to say Stephen with a P.H. my whole life.
More recent.
I've been able to say Stephen with a PhD nice but but mostly so I'm sure that poor angel
has to keep saying it's our Fouca Tonos with a pH with it over and over and over again.
We're just trying to put an F in there.
Yeah.
Okay.
Bevoros.
Baby.
Okay, baby
Who is
not the bat demon of Gotham City, by the way, no. Barbatos and
Beboros are not the same. Okay. And Zebulon. Yeah, not Zebulon,
but Zebulon, Zebulion, Zebulion, I think we should area. We'll
pronounce it that way. Zebulion. Yeah. Right. And you can and
you can rhyme it with cerulean as well. I mean, think of the
poetry kids. I mean, these are killer. So big.
time. And as one would expect, this is fundamental apocalypse territory. Ezra gets taken on a
tour of heaven and hell. I mean, you would not want an apocalypse without that. Right.
But see, remember I said to hold on to this Ezra element. Within the context of this tour,
or ask God questions, the questions God sort of like the first
three visions in 4th Ezra. This is like an Ezra theme. And basically his questions are
twofold. So the first question is he asked God why God allows humans to sin and bring
all this evil and wickedness into the world. And God's answer is that he's given humans
free will. And because he's given humans free will.
they are able to sin and bring all of this evil and suffering into the world.
As for a second question is a little less politically correct in that he says,
yeah, okay, you gave men free will,
but you also created women and the devil.
A little too pandora that you created even the serve.
and they seduced men into evil. So slightly less politically correct. But God's answer
to that is yes, he did create women in the devil, but he also took flesh and died on the
to grant forgiveness of sins and to destroy death.
So again overtly Christian
So that sets a theme
We're going to only briefly so there's a couple other similar sort of similar tax
One is called the vision of Ezra and what is called the questions of Ezra. Those are both medieval texts
Yeah later
And both involve the same kind of thing. It's basically Ezra questioning God about the Odyssey
Yeah.
The quote-unquote problem of evil, right?
And so that's this theme that's attached to Ezra.
But I hope you're seeing here that even into the medieval period, but all through Christian
history, Ezra is this prominent figure who keeps getting used in these texts as the
figure interacting with God.
They're not writing Job soon to pick a friend.
Yeah.
interesting.
I mean, he's clearly a big deal and like a fascinating figure for centuries upon centuries. Yeah
So then
So we can leave on a note of sheer weird
What I'm about to do to you is is is gonna be the the ancient textual equivalent of
Throwing a deck of cards at you and telling you to play 52 pickup, but here we go
We have a text from the 9th century. It's a Christian text
It's called the revelation of Ezra
Which I mean that's not confusing at all because revelation of course is
apocalypses
Yes, it's another yet another apocalypse of Ezra
This is the revelation of Ezra and this is not actually an apocalypse though. It's not a tour of heaven in hell
There is no Psycho Pop here. Yeah. No. This is basically a weird almanac.
Huh. A weird pharma's almanac. This is a genre of ancient literature. So today's secret word, kids,
when you hear it screamer aloud is calendar logian. I'm sorry, the Pee-Wee's Playhouse
Let's rip it through me off.
with a K. That's right. Yes. Now you can probably see the root of calendar in there. Yes. And
Logan, like book, like our menologian, the book of the months, right? Is the calendar
log in the book of the calendar. But how the revelation of Ezra works is based on what
day of the week, the new year and various Christian feasts fall on in a given year.
feasts fall on in a given year.
Okay, it predicts things like the weather and crop yields
Anything else
General fertility all those kind of things right yeah, I mean that's super farmers almanac. Yes. Yes, okay
And you may say well, that's just this weird one. I feel like it. No, this is a genre of ancient literature
there are a bunch of these
right and
And they start in the Jewish world, in the pre-Christian Jewish world, and they continue
in the Christian world, well into the medieval period, okay?
So two of the earliest examples we have are, one of them is the treatise of Shem, which
is a Jewish text from the first century B.C., okay?
And this text does b-
It's a Kellendilogian. It does basically the same thing. It predicts stuff like crop yields and weather and all of these things that are of importance to an agrarian culture.
Based on which zodiac sign is ascended on Rosh Hashanah?
Well, that's super astrology kind of stuff.
On the new year. Yes. We've done some stuff on Jewish astrology, right?
Well, you know, in my former town of Emmaus, Pennsylvania, they always said that you should
on what they called Housatog, which the day of of Jan Hus, Father Stephen, there you go.
That is the day in which you should plant turnips in Emmaus, Pennsylvania on Housatog.
So that's some hyper local lore for everybody out there.
By the way, Emmaus is three square miles.
They continue to be part of this.
grand tradition indeed yeah I mean I'm gonna be looking for stuff like that in
my new my new digs so but possibly the weirdest ancient version of this this is
what we're gonna close on here is a text called for Q cryptic which is also the
name of my next band and when you hear that Q that's right kumran this is a
a dead sea scroll. All right. We love a good game for spirits. Yeah, for
Q found in cave four of the Dead Sea Scrolls cryptic because they looked at it and went
what this text based on the Jewish text in the Dead Sea Scrolls Kubrod community based
on which astrological sign is ascendant when a baby is born it predicts their physiognomy.
I mean, that is outright astrology.
in the modern sense, almost just about. But here's the thing that seems so easily disprovable,
which means at least some large percentage of the time it must have been correct.
Yeah, because otherwise people like this doesn't work.
Yes. There you go. Four Q cryptic.
Four Q cryptic.
Your new favorite Dead Sea Scroll.
Yeah. Well, I, you know, actually most of what I was planning to say here at the end, I at some
point or another, I said in a couple of mini rants earlier in the episode, but I just want to just
to reiterate what to me I think is one of the most important takeaways from this briefly, is that
Orthodox tradition is not a big encyclopedia that you can look stuff up in. It's the living
experienced living tradition of the church where
where people actually have to live with each other and we have bishops in charge and things
that we do, feasts that we celebrate, it's not a code of law.
And I think that exploring all of these Ezra traditions really, really just kind of explodes
that idea out there, not in the sense of, you know, something blowing up, but but
But, you know, it lays it all out as kind of a big set of, you know, like maps, almost.
It just shows how incredibly varied all this stuff is.
Like, even just ask the question about about Ezra traditions.
What exactly is the canonical text?
What is canonical?
Are there multiple texts?
How do you understand them?
Who cites them?
In what way, like all of us and what's in them that gets all that stuff is just
soon.
Incredibly varied and that's okay for us orthodox because we're not a religion that's derived from a set of texts
We we are
To put it the other way we are religion that has texts
You know and we do different things with different texts and sometimes in different periods of history
We do different things with them
Not everything is always authoritative in the same way at the same time in the same place
You know like I made
earlier, for instance, to people kind of absolutizing liturgical texts. This is
wrong. This is wrong, everybody. It just, you can't absolutize liturgical texts in
that way. Just as an example, for instance, Orthros, you know, Mattens used to be
really dominated by what we're called Kentucky. Now we think of Kentucky now
as one short little hymn, but like, for instance, the Kentucky in St. Romanos,
that is the most famous one, is the Acathas to the Theotokos. That whole
long bit of poetry that across a bit of poetry that's based on the 24
letters of the Greek alphabet. That's a Kandakian. That used to be the thing that dominated Orthros. Now it's the Canon.
There's a sort of poetry called the Canon and the Kandakian is one little bit.
So it happened. Like if you're gonna say that that's the dogma of the church,
did it cease being dogma when we stopped using Kandakian that way?
And the Canon is now the new dogma. However many Kandans are gonna be, you know,
sung and recited in Orthros. Like it's just not.
That doesn't mean that the orthodox faith is this amorphous thing that
just be redefined and redefined or whatever. It means that the Holy Spirit is present in the church
vivifying it to keep the Orthodox faith and expressing it in different ways, different times,
different places, and that's okay. That's how this thing works. Orthodox Christianity is not
a religion that you can have like a whole library of books on yourself and just look
up everything and just kind of do it all at home. Or worse yet, you know, take that
library books until the
people how they're supposed to do it. It's just not. It's just not it's an actual living
community and the the glorious mess that is the set of texts going by the name of Ezra
as dress, you know, whatever. It really kind of illustrates that in an amazing and frankly
kind of fun way. So yeah, that's that's what I have to say.
So I'm going to kind of...
build off that right so as we mentioned one of these themes that emerges in a
lot of the Ezra literature that we were talking about in the in the third half is
this theme of Ezra sort of questioning God about his providence right about
his governance of his creation and wanting answers.
wanting to sort of understand things, and I think people are too quick to brush off the
response that he gets off in here, and that Job kind of gets at the end of Job of, you
know, tiny human you can't understand is like, oh, that's a punt, right? That's a, it's
not actually, because...
As much as we have the drive to understand and believe me right like that drive is very alive in me
Why do you think I keep getting all these pieces of paper to hang on my wall?
Wanting to understand everything we want to understand and comprehend things and and
Contained within that is a great deal of hubris a
Great deal of pride and arrogance to think that we can
I'm up to the task. I can understand everything if something doesn't make sense to me that it must not make sense at all
Or I just need to get to the bottom of it and then I will understand that I will comprehend that will all fit together for me
Then I can neatly categorize everything. I can put everything in boxes these neat little boxes and
That idea is related to the whole issue that we talked about in the second half with canonicity too
We want these neat little boxes these
are the scriptures. These are the canonical books. These are the authoritative books.
So their books are not those people who think that they are are wrong. And here are the arguments
that prove them wrong. And we will go and play the great game of going back and forth
about it for all eternity, arguing with each other, trying to score points and dunk
on each other. And the reality is that's not the way the world is. That's not
That's not the way life is, that's not the way reality is.
Life and reality don't fit into neat little boxes.
Boxes that can be checked off, boxes that can be labeled,
boxes that can be understood and contained and manipulated by us
as much as in our pride and our arrogance we want it to be.
Other people can't just be labeled and put in boxes
and, okay, now I understand this person.
know who this person is. I know what our relationship is. I can categorize it. I can define it.
I can... Obviously that's not true. To me, you have to be either a very young or very naive
person to even think it's true, right? Because when you get as old as I've gotten, there's
been a thousand times where you've been proven wrong, when you put a label on something,
when you thought you understood something, when you thought you had something contained
event.
whatever that is, it gets blown up. You're saying, oh, I was wrong. Oh, I didn't
understand what I thought I understood. Oh, I thought I had made sense of it, but
maybe it doesn't make sense, or maybe I'm just not up to understanding it. I just
need to trust and I just need to go with the flow. I just need to follow God
without necessarily understanding all the details.
We want this sort of security that comes from the idea that we understand we know what the threats are
We know where the fences are we've got it all under control
We don't we never do
There are times when we're able to fool ourselves into thinking we do and then those get blown up
And then we have anxiety and frustration and meltdowns and breakdowns and question our faith and question everything
Right, but that's all whiplash
From the pride and the arrogance that made us think that we have
it all understood and we had it all down and we had it all under control. So what I hope some
folks can take away from this is just to let go a little, to let things be what they are
without having to categorize everything, without having to put everything in a box,
especially God.
receive what God has for us to make our way through life following Him without having to
understand everything, without having to have all the guidelines, without having to, I need
to be clear on what the rules are, what are the rules, right?
There don't have to be rules.
There can just be life and doing your best, struggling against the worst parts of yourself
and not having to categorize.
it as always. This was a victory. This was a defeat. I'm a good person. I'm a bad person.
Right? You're a person. And you continue to struggle. And you do what you can do.
And you love God. And you love the people God has put in your life. And you make your way
through life. You don't have to understand it all. You won't. You can't. And you'll drive
yourself nuts trying to.
If you don't become humble enough to accept that fact, so that's my
Final thoughts. Amen for this evening. Amen. Well, happy six years of Lord of spirits podcast everybody. I can't believe we made it this far
Thanks for listening. If you didn't happen to get through to us live this time around
We'd still like to hear from you. You can email us Lord of spirits ancient faith comm you can message us at the Facebook page
You can also leave us a voicemail at speakpipe.com slash lord of spirits
And if you have basic questions about orthodox Christianity or you need help to find a parish in 3d go to orthodox intro dot
Org and join us for our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 6 p.m.
Eastern 3 p.m. Pacific looking around the house hidden behind the window in the door
Searching for signs of life, but there's nobody home
If you're on Facebook, you can follow our page, you can join our big...
Discussion group and leave us, you know reviews like some of the ones I read during this episode and share this show with one of your friends
Probably be sure to go to ancientfaith.com stroke support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air
Well, maybe I'm just too sure or maybe I'm just too frightened by the sound of it
Pieces of note fall down
But the letter said thank you. Good night. God bless you. You've been listening
to the Lord of Spirits, with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damoc and Father
Stephen DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beasts,
and the elders, and the number of them was ten thousand times ten thousand, and thousands
of thousands, saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain to receive
power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor.
in the glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.